每个人都有他的过去
Every person has a past, be it good or bad.
不管是好的还是坏的
而且每个城市也都是一样
It's the same with every city.
我现在所讲的
The story I'm about to tell
就是一个城市过去的故事
is about a certain city's past
而且过去很久了
a long, long time in the past.
七十二家房客
The House of 72 Tenants
马路不平，电灯不亮
The roads are uneven, the lights are dim,
自来水也不清
and the tap water's mucky.
你神经病
Damn this crazy tap!
上海婆，这么早洗头？
Washing your hair so early, Shanghai Po?
洗个死人头，这个水龙头发神经
Wash with what? This tap's gone crazy!
四妹啊
Fourth Sister!
劳你驾拿个水桶过来
Could you please bring over a bucket
跟我霸占一个位子
and claim me a place in the queue?
等一会来洗呀
I'll come back to wash later.
大块头
Hey, Big Guy!
你大清早去游水去了
Been swimming so early in the morning?
游你个头，我是被水淋湿的
Swimming my foot! I got soaked!
你还在这儿干什么？
What are you standing here for?
快拿衣服给送出去
Go deliver the clothes already!
拿了钱好去换大头，快啊！
Get the money and change it to HK dollars!
去啦，去啦
All right, I'm going!
杨伯，这么早就出去做生意
Uncle Yeung, off to work so early?
臭虫多得能把人抬起
How can I sleep with all the bugs in my bed?
怎么能睡得着了
是啊
True!
我欠你一包烟钱还没给你
I still owe you for the cigarettes.
上海佬，算你买了便宜货了
You got them cheap, Shanghai Man.
早！
Morning!
这点钱今天只能买六根烟
This much will only buy 6 cigarettes today.
改天再多给你点儿
I'll pay the extra some other time.
不用，天天涨价，关你什么事？
It's OK. Prices rise daily. Not your fault.
韩师母早！     早！
Morning Mrs Han! - Morning!
怎么，你作天又熬通宵啊
Been working all night again?
是！
Yes!
快点上去吧
You better go upstairs quickly.
你们韩先生昨天又咳嗽了一夜
Mr. Han was coughing all night again.
谢谢
Thank you!
大学毕业生
College graduate!
你还没睡？
Haven't you gone to bed yet?
没有，我想赶完这篇稿子去报馆
No, I want to finish this for the paper.
你还不去睡
Why aren't you asleep yet?
我买了点药回来，先去煎给你喝
I bought some medicine. I'll fix it for you.
韩师母早！
Good morning, Mrs. Han!
早！
Morning!
韩先生大学毕业到现在一直失业
Mr Han's an unemployed university graduate.
韩师母念完书又去做舞女
After classes, Mrs Han works as a hostess.
这是个什么世界
What sort of world is this?
我看你也好不到那儿去
I reckon you're no better!
快去排队拿水       好
Quick! Go line up for water! - OK.
这个给你玩
Here's something for you to play with.
福哥，这么早就开工啊！
Off to work so early, Brother Fook?
是了，陈伯
That's right, Uncle Chan.
你也知道，早点卖了，早点回家
The sooner it's sold, the sooner I'm home.
如果去晚一点
The later I go to Boss Chin's
拿这些现钞到钱老板去换大头
to exchange this cash,
差好多呢？
the fewer HK dollars it's worth!
阿福啊！     什么事？
Ah Fook! - What is it?
你还不去看看
Go see if the cheongsam's dry yet.
那件旗袍干了没有？
是，老婆大人
Yes, almighty wife!
小福怎么样？
How's Little Fook?
好像还有一点点发烧
He still seems to have a slight temperature.
不要紧，等我回来带他去看医生
I'll take him to the doctor when I'm back.
早！
Morning!
上海婆      阿香回来了
Shanghai Po. - Ah Heung, you're back.
对了，肥皂又涨价了
Yes. Soap's gone up again.
昨天这些钱能买两条
I could have bought two bars yesterday
今天只能买一条了
for the same price as one today!
这种日子叫我怎么过啊？
How will I ever get through times like these?
上海婆啊！水来了没有
Shanghai Po, is there water yet?
来了，在发神经病
It's coming. Damn crazy tap!
算了，我先上去拿个桶排队
I'll go get a bucket and queue up.
好，你要快点啊！
You better hurry.
上海婆      早！
Shanghai Po. - Good morning!
金医生，你早！
Good morning, Dr Kim.
上海婆，给我熨熨裤子
Could you iron my trousers please?
真的吗，金医生
Really, Dr Kim?
你搬来这么久，还是第一次出诊
Your first house call since moving here!
没办法，从山东到此地来
Can't be helped. Moving here from Shantung,
人生路不熟
I don't know anyone around here.
再说做医生要靠运气的
Besides, even a doctor needs luck.
对了，金医生，这回出诊
This time, Dr Kim, you should charge more.
怎么也得收贵点了
不…那不行，做医生要有医德
No, I couldn't. A doctor must have ethics.
我在山东的时候
In Shantung, I never charged the poor.
穷人看病不要钱的
好，那我先挂个号了
In that case, I'll register with you!
不过像我们这些穷人
But a poor people like me
情愿死也不愿意生病
would rather die than be sick.
对了，我先跟你熨裤子了
So, I'd better go iron your trousers.
谢谢      不用
Thank you. - Don't mention it.
老婆啊！
Oh, wifey!
你看，浆糊又给老鼠吃光了
Look. The rats have eaten up the paste again.
那怎么办？
What are we going to do?
到和记去借半碗面粉再打一碗
Borrow some flour from Wo Kee to make more.
不成，上次借的我们还没还呢
We can't. We still owe them from last time.
明儿一块再还吧
We'll give it all back tomorrow.
没浆糊怎么干活啊？
How can I work without glue?
四妹     早！
Fourth sister. - Morning!
有面粉吗？
Do you have any flour?
刚用完了，爸爸去买还没回来
Just ran out. But dad's gone to buy some.
陈嫂，浆糊给老鼠吃光了
Mrs Chan, the rats got at the paste again?
是啊！
Yes!
爸爸，怎么只有半袋面粉啊
How come there's only half a bag of flour?
你不知道呀，又涨价了
Don't you know, the price went up again.
昨天的钱可以买一袋
The price of a whole bag yesterday
今天买半袋
could only buy half a bag today!
这生意怎做呀
How are we going to stay in business?
那我们也可以一样
We can do the same.
把油条炸少一点
We can always make our fritters thinner.
现在我们的油条
They're already thin as chopsticks now.
都已经像油炸筷子了
再炸小一点不成油炸牙签
Any thinner and they'll be toothpicks!
陈嫂，是不是要面粉打浆糊？
Mrs Chan, didn't you say you need some flour?
现在不用了
No, I don't need it anymore.
来，来
Come on,
没有浆糊怎么作活呢？
How can a tailor work without paste?
不行了，不行了
No, no.
水来了，水来了
The water's coming! The water's coming!
四妹啊
Fourth Sister!
麻烦你拿个桶先帮我装点水吧！
Please get a bucket and fetch me some!
来，来
Come on.
阿香，我想先用你让让我好不好
Ah Heung, could you let me go first?
好
Sure.
你等着用，那我先给你吧！
You need it right away. You go ahead.
谢谢
Many thanks!
楼下关水龙头，你们想造反啊
Turn it off downstairs! Is this a rebellion?
明知道我起床要洗脸
You know very well I need to wash my face!
干么把水开得那么大
And yet you turn on the tap full blast!
我们怎知道你起床
How are we to know you just got up?
而且水刚来，我们还没装够呢
Anyway, we haven't drawn our fill yet.
妈的，一大早你们就气我啊
Giving me grief first thing in the morning!
好，我下去给你们点厉害看看
Damn it! I'll come down and show you.
妈下来了，怎么办？
Ma's coming down. What shall I do?
怕什么，又不关你的事
So what? It's got nothing to do with you.
我…
I...
怕怕怕什么，干么怕她
What are you so afraid of her for?
不许用，你们他妈的
You're not allowed to use it, damn it!
什么时候用完才能轮到我洗脸
How long do I have to wait to wash my face?
八姑！八姑你这也不对
That's not fair, Pat Koo.
你这可就强词夺理了
You're being unreasonable.
你不是装了条私人水管子
Didn't you install a personal water pipe?
对呀！
That's right!
什么私人水管子
What do you mean "personal"?
你们把水开得这么大
With you turning on the tap full blast,
水怎么冲得上去啊
how can any water get up there?
妈，我现在不是在排队接水吗？
Ma, can't you see I'm already queuing?
你还嘴硬呀，昨天晚上我吩咐你
Shut up! I told you last night to come early.
早点下来排队，怎么才排第二
How come you're second in the queue?
你别动手，是阿香让给我的
Don't hit her. Ah Heung let me go first.
是你让给别人
You let someone else go first!
你明知我等水洗脸
When you know I need water for washing!
你把水让给别人，你个死丫头
You stupid girl!
你要洗脸，我们楼上还有一大缸
We still have a big bucket upstairs.
关你们什么事
It's none of your business!
看我一会儿收拾你
Stupid girl! I'll fix you later!
还不滚回去，滚上去
Get the hell back upstairs!
他妈的
Damn it!
妈什么，我有水是我的事
What are you cursing about?
我还拿去卖呢？
It's my water. If I like, I can even sell it.
水啊，留着你自己去卖吧！
Right, you better sell it then!
去你妈的，你们听着
Damn the whole lot of you! Now listen!
我现在有个新的规矩
I'm making a new rule.
从明天开始等我用完了
From tomorrow, no one gets water
你们才能用
until after I've finished using it.
这就不对了
That's not right!
我们每个人都交一份水费的
We all pay a share of the water bill.
哎呀！
That's right!
你还好意思说，我问你
You dare bring that up? Let me ask you:
你交一份水费，你用多少水？
how much water do you use for your share?
你怎么不记得了
Don't you remember now?
我们不是讲好的吗
Didn't we agree on the matter?
我免费跟你洗熨衣服
I wash and iron your clothes for free
你才答应我用这么多的水的
in return for using so much water.
你不要紧的吧
If it's all the same to you, fine!
好，以后我就不用你替我洗熨
I don't need you to wash and iron from now on.
好呀
Fine!
你们大家都听着
Now listen, all of you!
我规定由现在开始
From now on, the rule is each household
每一家，每一户，只许用一桶水
can only have one tub of water a day.
那怎么行？
No way!
真他妈的滚蛋！
Damn that bloody bitch!
阿福！
Ah Fook!
我马上就回来
I'll be right back.
真是多管闲事
Why don't you mind your own business?
你这不是明明对付我吗？
You're deliberately targeting me!
我们开洗衣店的
We run a laundry!
一天一桶水怎么够啊
How can a tub of water a day be enough?
不用怕，上海婆
Don't worry, Shanghai Po,
我白杬福帮助你
I, Olive Vendor Fook, am on your side.
臭小子，口气倒不小
Big talk, little man.
我看你怎么帮助她
What good are you going to do her?
我省点，我每天给你半桶水
I can spare you half of my daily water.
对，对
Right, right.
你们造反啊？你们造反啊？
What's this, a rebellion? A rebellion?
是不是，上海婆，你怕什么？
See? There's nothing to fear.
这儿有七十二家人
There are 72 tenants here.
每天就有三十六桶水
That's 36 buckets of water a day.
你开茶馆都够啊     谢谢
Enough even for a restaurant! -Thank you!
八姑，听见了没有
Hear that, Pat Koo?
以后你的衣服要自己洗自己烫啦
You'll have to wash your own clothes now!
我们还是继续排队接水
We'll continue lining up for water,
我现在要跟金医生烫裤子
and I'll go iron Dr Kim's pants.
水满了你们帮我关就可以了
When my tub's full, please turn it off.
肥婆
Fat pig!
八姑，告诉你
Pat Koo, let me tell you,
有时做人就不能做得太绝
one should never push people too far.
好比说，八姑你做事不应该
You'll get your comeuppance
独占水喉报应就要来
if you try to hog the water for yourself.
阿福，你快点回来吧
Ah Fook, come back here.
喝了粥该做生意了
Have some congee and get to work.
八姑，我要回去喝粥，回头见
Eighth Aunt, I'm having congee. See you!
上海婆出来，出来
Come here, Shanghai Po!
你干嘛呀，我在熨裤子嘛？
What do you want? I'm ironing!
你真是，你干什么呀
What are you trying to do?
我八姑是出了名的骂大街的
I'm known as the battleaxe around here,
你来跟我找岔子，你什么意思？
and you dare pick a fight with me?
那是你自己找的
You picked the fight yourself.
劳驾你以后的衣服自己洗自己熨
Now you can wash and iron your own clothes.
熨，熨，熨，糟了
Iron...iron...iron...oh no!
糟糕！糟糕！这是金医生的裤子
Oh no! These are Dr Kim's trousers!
他只有就么一条裤子
They're the only pair he has!
还等着出诊呢
And he has a housecall to make!
现在破了，这怎么呢？
They're ruined! What do I do now?
上海婆，这就恭喜你了
Congratulations, Shanghai Po!
这是善有善报，恶有恶报
As you sow, so shall you reap!
你看金医生的这条裤子
See how nicely you've ironed
给你熨得多漂亮
Dr Kim's trousers!
上海婆、上海婆
Shanghai Po! Shanghai Po!
我的裤子熨好了吗？
Are my trousers ready?
我…
I...
熨好了，而且熨得见膀呢
Ironed crisply, all ironed to a crisp.
什么贝粉，还卤玉米呢？
What do you mean, ironed to a crisp?
好香啊
Smells good, too.
上海婆，等会回来再给你钱
Shanghai Po, I'll pay you later.
金医生啊，你看看你这条腿啊
Dr Kim, look at your leg.
上海婆，你可真害苦我了
Shanghai Po! What have you done?
我只有这一条裤子
This is my only pair of trousers!
第一次出诊，不穿裤子怎么行呢
My first housecall, and I have no trousers!
金医生，其实也不关我的事
Dr Kim, it's not really my fault!
都是那个骚货
It's all because of that bitch!
我正在熨裤子
Picking a quarrel while I was ironing!
她硬把我拉出来吵架
你熨坏人家裤子怎么来怪我
You burned his pants. Don't blame me!
这就不对了
That's not right!
我们大伙都看见
We all saw it.
你把她拉来吵架的，你还赖呀
You dragged her out. Don't deny it!
关你什么事？
What business is it of yours?
不错，是我叫她出来
That's right, I did call her out,
可没叫她熨坏人家的裤子
I didn't tell her to burn the pants!
不过我也讲一句公道话
But I can say a fair word too:
你要她赔
if you want compensation,
这帮穷鬼是怎样也赔不起了
there's no way this pauper can pay up.
不过那条裤子是谁的
so it's just hard luck to Dr Kim!
谁就活该倒霉
八姑啊，你还说风凉话
Pat Koo, what a thing to say!
其实说起来这条裤子应该你赔
Actually, you should pay for the trousers.
什么？
What?
对，你赔
Yes, you should pay.
不要吵！
Shut up!
你们想造反啊？
What's this, a rebellion?
你们这帮王八蛋
You bunch of bastards!
一大清早想多睡一会都不行，吵…
Making so much noise in the morning!
什么事？
What's going on?
这个上海婆
This Shanghainese woman
熨坏人家裤子她们想要我赔
wants me to pay for trousers she burnt!
你讲不讲理你
What sort of reasoning is that?
你熨坏别人的裤子叫我赔
You burn someone's pants, and I should pay?
赔什么赔？
Pay on what basis?
别说不是我太子炳熨的
I wasn't the one who burned the pants,
就是我熨坏的
and even if I was,
我不想赔的话我就是不赔
I wouldn't pay if I don't feel like it!
真是太不讲道理的
How unreasonable can you get?
山东佬
Shantung Man,
你的裤子要是怕给别人熨坏的
if you don't want your pants burnt,
你别拿给别人熨
you should iron them yourself!
这是天灾人祸，各安天命
It's an accident, an act of God,
这还有什么好说的
what more is there to be said?
哎，我只有一条裤
But these are the only trousers I have!
还等着出诊呢？
And I still have a housecall to make!
你等上吊也没有用，坏都坏了
Well, it's no use crying over split milk.
我告诉你，你算是走运啦
I tell you, you should count yourself lucky.
要是裤子被人偷了
If they'd been stolen instead,
连渣都没有啊？
you wouldn't have anything left!
你看不是挺好的吗
See? Isn't that fine?
把它改成短裤
You can turn them into a pair of shorts.
跟童子军一样，多神奇
Just like the Boy Scouts. Marvellous!
同时现在天热，穿短裤多凉快嘛
Shorts are ideal for this hot weather.
糟了，我这儿还有一条裤子
Oh no. My son only has one pair of pants.
这是我的裤子吗
Are these mine?
你看…还有个金字
Look...there's my name, Kim!
我跟你说，你要倒起霉来
Like I said, when a man's unlucky,
好好的裤子
even his trousers will lose a leg.
两条腿会变成一条腿
熨破了，那还不活该呢
You can't blame anyone else
你看他那德性，还有得倒霉呢
He's got more bad luck coming.
对呀！
How true!
周炳根，糟了，炳哥
Chow Bing-Ken. Oh no! Brother Bing!
知不知呀这是你的
Do you know this is yours?
阿炳，糟糕了
Ah Bing! This was made 2 days ago!
这条裤子前两天才做的
上海婆，你别溜
Shanghai Po, stay where you are!
我告诉你，你赔我的裤子
I'll sue you! You'll pay me back!
我要你赔我妈的
You'll bloody well pay me back!
炳哥，你要怕人熨烂裤子
Ah Bing, if you don't want your pants burnt,
就别找人熨
you should iron them yourself!
这叫天灾人祸，各安天命
It's an accident, an act of God,
没得赔
why should anyone pay?
幸好没被人家偷了去
Count yourself lucky they weren't stolen,
要是被人家偷去就连渣都没了
otherwise you'd have nothing left!
现在多好，把它改成短裤
But now you can turn them into shorts,
像童子军一样多神气，又凉快
just like the Boy Scouts. Cool too!
对不起，我要拿药箱出诊了
Excuse me, I must go make my housecall.
你怎么拿裤子给那该死的熨啊？
Why give the pants to that damn woman?
不是我给她熨的吗
I didn't!
是我叫阿香自己熨的吗
I told Ah Heung to iron it!
阿香     来啦
Ah Heung! - Coming!
妈，什么事啊！
What is it, ma?
我问你，谁叫你把裤子给上海婆熨
Who told you to give the pants to her?
不是你叫我的吗？
You did!
你说给上海婆洗是不要钱的
You said Shanghai Po does it for free,
你还说这点便宜不占
and only a fool wouldn't take advantage.
简直是王八蛋
Godammit! Stupid girl, I'll kill you!
你这死丫头，我非打死你…
住手，不许打
Hold it! Don't hit her!
你怎么啦
What's the matter with you?
他叫你不要动你就不要动
He tells you to stop and you stop.
你那么听话
Why are you so obedient?
站着跟个死人一样
Standing there like a zombie!
死小子，你是谁？
Who are you, you damned kid?
我是谁，你们听着
Who am l? Listen well.
我就是这条街九十六号门牌
I live at No. 96 on this street,
上海婆隔壁，包租婆楼下
next to Shanghai Po, below the landlady,
公共楼梯的左边
to the left of the communal staircase,
潮州卖烟佬房间里
in the Chiu Chow cigarette vendor's room,
弄在墙上的那个床铺
on the bunk you fixed halfway up the ceiling.
发记补鞋的发仔
I'm Fat Chai, the cobbler,
我也是这儿七十二家房客之一
one of the 72 tenants here as well.
怎么这个人我不认识他？
Why haven't I seen this guy before?
他搬过来没几天
He only moved in a few days ago.
那就难怪
No wonder.
小飞，你知不知道我是谁？
Do you know who I am, kid?
不知道
No.
那我告诉你
Then, let me tell you.
我是这儿包租婆八姑的丈夫
I'm the husband of the landlady, Pat Koo.
我在这附近上至八十岁的老头子
Everyone around here,
下至三岁的鼻涕虫
from 80 year-old codgers to tiny tots of 3,
东至东山、西至西村
east to Tungshan, west to West Village,
南至河南、北到火车站
south to Henan, north to the train station,
那个不知道我太子炳啊？
everyone knows me, Master Bing!
就是我不知道
Everyone except me.
你这死小子
God damned kid!
我管女儿你也管得着
How I treat my daughter's not your business!
我当然管得着
Of course it's my business!
我是路见不平，拔刀相助
I must defend the weak against the strong!
什么？
What?
路见不平，拔刀相助啊
Defend the weak against the strong?
你知不知道阿香是什么人？
Do you know what Ah Heung is?
女人
She's a woman.
那你是什么人？
And what are you?
男人
A man!
你是她的男人
You're her man?
你这该死的，管闲事管到我头上
You bloody kid, poking your nose in!
等我先问清楚了
Let me get this straight!
你这死小子，你把话说明白点
Let's be clear about this, you bloody kid!
你说什么？
What are you saying?
阿香是你的女人
That Ah Heung's your woman
你是阿香的男人
and you're her man?
这还用问，你们听清楚了
Why ask? You all heard clearly.
我问你，我是男人还是女人？
Let me ask you. Am I a man or a woman?
当然是男人啦
A man of course!
阿香是男人还是女人？
Is Ah Heung a man or a woman?
当然是女人了
Of course she's a woman!
这不解了吗
Then isn't it settled? Just now I said
我刚才说我是男人，阿香是女人
that I'm a man and Ah Heung's a woman.
我还说错了，真是笨蛋
And you say I got it wrong. Idiot!
你这个王八蛋，我非打死他不可
You son of a bitch, I'll kill you!
你别动手
Stop it!
你别打，叫他们来
Stop it! Tell them to come!
不能打架，不能打架
Don't fight! Don't fight!
不要打
我用铁沙掌来打他
I'll use my lron Palm on him!
不要打
Don't fight!
不要打，算了吧
Don't fight! Forget it!
帮他打
Help him!
铁沙掌你不怕，你看我的太极拳
Not afraid of lron Palm? Try my Tai-Chi!
发神经
You're crazy!
起来，起来
Get up! Get up!
不要打
Don't fight!
好小子，你等着瞧
Damned kid! You wait and see!
我的绝招还没有弄呢
I haven't used all my kung fu yet!
你看我的猴拳
Try my Monkey Fist!
算！算！别打了
Forget it! Stop fighting!
不打     别理他们
Stop fighting! -Forget about them.
不理他们
Forget about them.
别理他们这帮穷鬼
Forget this bunch of penniless beggars.
我告诉你，我这个瓷器
I'm telling you, I'm not demeaning myself
绝不跟你们这些烂缸瓦碰
by crossing swords with you peasants!
怎样，你怎样
What? What?
回去吧！走
Let's go! Go!
回去！    好
Go! - All right.
好小子，你走着瞧！
Just you wait, you damned kid!
我下次再碰到你，我绝不饶你
You won't be so lucky the next time!
你去哪？
Where are you going?
你没事吧？
Are you all right?
他怎能打着我
He didn't touch me.
你没事吧？
Are you all right?
没事，幸亏有你
Yes, thanks to you.
喂，你们别走，我的布料丢了
Hey, don't go! I lost a piece of fabric.
你别管闲事，你快回去吧！
None of your business. Go!
不管怎么行
How can l?
谁知是真是假
Who knows if it's for real or not?
真要命！
Damn it!
阿炳！
Ah Bing!
老婆，老婆，我们的衣料丢了
Wife, we lost a piece of fabric.
什么时候丢的？
How did that happen?
就是炳哥和发仔打架时丢的
It vanished during the fight.
那怎办呢？
What do we do?
你丢了衣料是真的还是假的？
Have you lost it for real?
还是在胡说八道啊！
Or are you just making it up?
当然是真的了
Of course it's for real!
那块衣料跟这块一模一样
The fabric looks exactly like this one.
是四婶让我做两件旗袍
It's for making two cheongsams
给她的双胞胎穿的
for Fourth Aunt's pair of twins.
好啦…别说了，大家别走
Say no more. Everybody stay where you are.
现在我要一个个儿的搜
I'm searching you one by one.
如果在谁的身上
Whoever the fabric's found on
搜出这块衣料来
will have to compensate us all
那我们以前丢的东西
for everything we ever lost.
全由他一个人赔
不过这样，如果搜到的话
And if the loot turns up,
就让他烧一只猪来还神
Iet him roast a pig to thank the gods
还得请十桌酒请大伙来喝喝
and hold a banquet for all the tenants.
要十桌酒，那我们不搜了
That's too much. Forget it!
算了，不要了，算了
Forget it! Forget it!
算了，算了！
你们算了我可不能够算了
You can forget it, but I can't.
我丢的东西实在是太多了
I've lost too much already.
如果在他身上能够搜着的话
If I find the thief,
我就让这小子一个人赔
he will have to compensate me!
你别这么瞎指
Don't talk nonsense.
我问你，你丢了什么东西？
Let me ask you, what have you lost?
我丢的东西太多
Too much!
一个金表，两条三斤重的金链
A gold watch, two 3-catty gold chains...
三斤重？你不怕坠断你的脖子
3 catties? That woud break your neck!
关你什么事？
What business is it of yours?
老子的脖子能够顶得住
My neck's strong enough!
还有四套西装，五件旗袍
Also 4 suits, 5 cheongsams,
六双鞋，七顶帽子，八张酸枝椅
6 pairs of shoes, 7 hats,
九长床单，还有十只金戒指
8 antique tables, 9 bedsheets, 10 gold rings,
还有一张沙发，五个五斗柜
1 sofa, and 5 chests of drawers.
这还算偷东西，这简直是搬家
That's no theft, it's moving house!
你多什么嘴，关你什么事？
Shut up! It's none of your business.
大家丢了什么东西赶快说了
Whoever's lost anything, speak up now.
如果搜出的话大家都没好处
It's no use speaking up after we find it.
快说，快说
Speak up, speak up.
阿炳，这又不关我们的事
Ah Bing, stay out of it.
我们还是回去吧！
Let's go home.
这是条财路的
It's a good way to make money
如果那个衣料
If I find the fabric on that damned kid,
在那小子身上搜出的话
什么棺材本，什么什么都有了吗
I can afford everything plus my coffin!
你随便说几样都可以
Just name a few things you've lost.
对了，八姑说她丢东西了
That's right, Pat Koo lost some things too.
你丢了什么了？
What did you lose?
没有     没有
Nothing. - Nothing?
五筒没有
Co...coal, 5 buckets of coal
你真是要我的命
Upon my life!
还有什么？
What else?
五只金戒指
Five gold rings.
这个王八蛋     阿福
You bastard. - Ah Fook.
阿炳
Ah Bing,
我看是找不到了
I don't think you'll find anything.
我们还是回去吧！
Let's go home.
怎么会找不到呢？
What makes you think we won't find anything?
大伙都听着了
Listen everyone.
那块布料就是这个颜色的
The fabirc is exactly this colour.
我搜给你们看
I'll conduct the search.
你蟑头鼠目的，先搜你   别动
You look suspicious. You first. -Hold it!
你搜我谁去搜你
You search me, who searches you?
我还用搜，我像贼吗？
Nobody. Do I look like a thief?
那块布料会在我身上搜到？
You think you'll find the fabric on me?
你神经病的
You're crazy!
谁知道你像不像贼
Who can tell if you're a thief or not?
要搜大家一块儿搜
If there's a search, we all do it!
好，大家搜
OK, let's all search!
搜不出来有你好看的
But if nothing turns up, you'll be sorry.
搜啊！
Let's search!
你干什么？
What are you doing?
我要搜他
I'm searching him.
炳啊，你跟他们讲话什么
Ah Ping, what are you talking with them for?
你又不会偷东西呢，走走，回去
You'd never steal. Let's go.
走开，男人大丈夫说得到做得到
Away! I'm a man of my word.
我又不是贼，我怕什么呀！
I'm no thief. I have nothing to fear.
是，搜，搜
Yes, search!
搜，搜
Search! Search!
你搜呀你！
You go search!
我自己搜，没有啊
I'll search myself! There's nothing.
没有
Nothing.
这个不会有
Won't be anything here.
原来他就是贼
So he's the thief!
还神摆酒…
Thank the gods! Hold a banquet!
这真是自找倒霉
You brought this on yourself.
老陈，你偷偷的嫁祸于我
Old Chan, you framed me!
把衣料放在我口袋里
You slipped it into my pocket!
阿福
Ah Fook!
你害我是不是？
You framed me, didn't you?
我说不是我啊！
I tell you it's not me!
还说不是你
You still deny it?
太子炳，你别冤枉好人
Master Bing, don't accuse an innocent person!
阿福
Ah Fook.
刚才打架的时候
During the fight just now,
我亲眼看见有人把这块衣料
I saw someone slip it into your pocket,
放在你口袋里的
不过不是陈伯
but it wasn't Uncle Chan.
你亲眼看见
You saw someone put it in my pocket?
有人把衣料放在我口袋里
阿福，我早就说过你很够聪明
Ah Fook, didn't I always say you were smart?
你是个好人
You're a decent person.
大伙都听清楚了没有
Did you all hear what he said?
有人看见他把衣料
Someone saw him slip the fabric
偷偷的放在我口袋里去的
into my pocket.
阿福，你看是哪个绝子绝孙的
Ah Fook, tell me which son of a bitch
把衣料放在我口袋里去的
planted the fabric in my pocket?
我要拧断他脖子，砸烂他的狗头
I'll wring his neck and bash his head!
活生生捏死他
I'll strangle him alive!
阿福哥
Brother Fook,
前两天我把你的电线给剪了
I cut your electricity a few days ago,
你一定很不方便
It must be such an inconvenience.
明天，我马上给你接好
I'll reconnect it first thing tomorrow.
这么好心？
How kind!
你当然明白我的意思了
Of course, you get my meaning.
我知道
Of course I get it.
炳哥，我现在不知道是谁了
Brother Bing, I can't tell now who it was.
你这是什么意思
What do you mean, you can't tell?
你不说出来
What do you mean, you cant tell?
我怎么去拧断他的脖子
How would I know whose neck to break?
你叫我说呀
You want me to tell?
不要说呀，你千万不要说是我
Don't! Don't tell him it's me!
你又不要我说呀？
And you don't want me to tell?
这就不对了，福哥
That's not right, Brother Fook.
你知道就该说出来
If you know, you should speak up,
大家好落个清白
so the rest of us are in the clear.
对了！
That's right!
还是说了好
I suppose I'd better tell.
我说了
It's her!
白杬福，你诚心要我塌台
Olive Peddler, you're deliberately doing this!
好，我叫三六九来对付你
OK! I'll have Constable 369 sort you out!
老板，给我来碗烧鹅米粉
Rice noodles with roast goose,
要大碗的
a big bowl of it,
一瓶白干，巷子里
and a bottle, in the alley.
敬礼！
Salute!
干什么？是我啊！
What are you doing? It's me!
太子炳，你别吓唬我好不好
Master Bing, don't scare me!
人吓人能吓死人呀
You could scare someone to death!
我吃东西是偷偷摸摸的
I have to hide in order to eat.
怎么样？不要钱的
How's this? It's free.
不要钱？那我也来一份
Free? In that case I'll have some.
好
Excellent!
老板，照样来一份啊！
The same again.
太子炳啊！你一定有事来找我
Something you need help with, Master Bing?
大的事可别来麻烦我
If it's serious, I don't want to know!
知道了，三六九明天你要给我
Understood. 369, tomorrow I want you
对付那个小贩白杬福
to sort out that olive peddler for me.
你要一包
You want a packet.
谢谢
Thanks.
给我二包
Give me two.
楼上也要
Upstairs.
钱呐      谢谢
Money's inside. - Thanks.
你也要
You want some?
来
Come.
福哥，我也来买，我要三包
Me too, Brother Fook. I'll have 3 packets.
要几包？
How many?
三包呀
Three packets!
谢谢！     谢谢你呀！
Thanks! - Thanks you!
福哥！
Brother Fook!
来，来，来
Come, come!
你也要！
You want some too?
先生啊！过来叫船吧！来呀！
Mister, come ride in my sampan.
那老总，叫船吗？
Hey Boss, you want a ride?
初四啊！
Hey, Fourth!
什么事，十五？
What is it, Fifteenth?
你那个米店老板来了
Your rice shop sugar daddy's coming.
初四
Fourth.
怎么这么早，程老板
How come you're so early, Boss Ching?
怎么敢迟
I dare not be late! Any later,
再迟你的船给人租走了
and someone else might have hired your boat.
别这样，昨晚我让你给气死了
Don't. You really annoyed me last night.
你给我的船钱
What? -The boat money you gave me.
我今天去换大头，亏了一半
I changed it today, and it's only worth half.
这回你放心
Relax.
今天我租船不给钱
I'm not paying you with money today.
那你给我什么？
Then what are you paying me with?
一担米
1 00 catties of rice.
这倒不错，下船吧！混球
Good idea! Come on in, hot shot.
你才混！      讨厌！
You're the one who's hot! -Disgusting!
来
Come.
十五啊！    什么事？
Fifteenth! -What is it?
先拿这些现钞去换大头吧！
Take this cash and change it to HK dollars.
这儿四十万，刚好四块！
There's 400 grand here: 4 bucks, exactly!
你是不是弄错了
What? Are you sure?
刚才那人给你大头就一块九万
That guy was paying 1 dollar to 90 grand.
我现在给你现钞就十万换一块
Now I'm giving you 100 grand cash to a buck.
这不差了一万块
Here's 10 thousand exactly.
就是这样了
That's how it is.
要不是左刮一点，右刮一点
You scrape a bit from left and right.
怎么能赚很多钱呢？
How else do you make money?
不过叔叔
But uncle,
我爹以前和你是结拜兄弟
my dad used to say you were blood brothers.
我告诉你吧，就算你是我爹
Let me tell you, even if it's my own father,
也要这么刮的
I'd be scraping all the same!
这件事情你别急呀
There's no use getting upset over this.
让我告诉你呀，谈到钱
I tell you, when it comes to money,
爹跟儿子也没得商量的
not even fathers and sons make a difference.
四块钱！
Four dollars!
抢劫啊！抢劫啊！
Thief! Thief!
有贼…巡警呀，有贼，跑了
Constable, there's a thief! He's run off!
有贼，没看见呀！
Thief? Where?
在那边     在哪边？好
There! -There? OK!
在那边儿啊！
No! He went that way!
你们几个丫头是不是疯了？
Are you crazy or what?
我是抓贼的吗？
Do I look like I chase thieves?
你不抓贼？
You don't?
卖橄榄的小子，你别走 三六九
You! Olive peddler! Halt! -369
我问你，刚才有人喊抢东西
369, I heard someone shout "thief".
你什么不去追贼？
Why aren't you chasing the thief?
玩命啊！我没听见，你去追吧
And risk my life? I didn't hear it. You go.
真是败类
How pathetic!
小姐，贼跑什么地方去了？
Miss, which way did the thief go?
他往那边去了     谢谢你
He went that way. -Thanks!
这个不错
This one's not bad.
警察有两种的！
Seems there're two kinds of policemen!
你是不是叫白杬福
Are you Fook, the olive peddler?
是的，我就是
Yes, I am.
进去，进去，走！
Inside. Move!
老兄，有什么事啊？
What's the matter, brother?
查牌
Licence check.
我这种流动营业的小生意
Where would a mobile small business like mine
那里有什么牌？
get any sort of licence?
凡是做生意的都要领牌
Every kind of business needs a licence.
为什么你不领
Why didn't you apply for one?
老兄，去领牌比要饭还要惨
Applying for a licence is worse than begging.
你们弟兄办事比蜗牛还慢
Your colleagues work slower than snails!
谁说的，你欠税试试看
Says who? You try dodging taxes,
追得你命都没有了，废话少说
then you'd know how fast they work.
跟我到警察局去
You're coming with me to the station.
有事情慢慢商量
Wait! Let's talk this over.
有商量，行！
OK, let's talk.
干嘛，看手相我不懂
What's this? I'm not a palm reader
看什么手相，是五斗米
It isn't palm reading, it's 5 pecks of rice.
五斗米，你给我
5 pecks? You're giving it to me?
怎么，没有呀？
Well? Do you have it or not?
当然没有啦
Of course not!
这样好了
How about this?
夏季大减价，三斗吧！
A summer discount: 3 pecks!
也没有
I don't have that much either.
又没有
You don't?
我看这样好了
Then this is what we'll do.
你就给我三块大头也行！
You can give me 3 HK dollars.
三块大头，你给我差不多
3 HK dollars! You must be kidding!
想不到你比我还要坏呀！
I didn't know you worse off than me!
那干干脆脆一块大头就行了
All right, let's settle it for a dollar.
想抢呀！
That's robbery!
我辛辛苦苦赚来的钱
It's hard-earned money!
还要养老婆儿女的
I've a wife and a kid to support!
你少啰嗦
Quit complaining!
有钱大家花，有福大家享
Money's meant to be shared.
你要是不给钱，我就抓你去坐牢
Pay up, or I lock you up.
他妈的，简直是打劫
Dammit! This is outight robbery!
福哥
Brother Fook.
什么事？
What's the matter?
你回来了
You're back!
小福病得很厉害
Your son's very ill!
你快去看看吧！
Go see him, quick!
福哥，小福发烧得很厉害
Ah Fook, Little Fook has a high fever.
金医生说他是急性肺炎
Dr Kim says it's acute pneumonia!
金医生说要马上送医院
He said we must take him to the hospital.
现在去问住院手续去了
He's gone to make the arrangements.
我老婆呢？     去借钱去了
Where's my wife? -Gone to borrow money.
别动，别动
Don't move. Don't move.
别动
这可是真货，三个大头
The real McCoy, 3 HK dollars!
下次多带点
Bring more next time.
走啦！
Go!
有贼！
Thief!
这个小流氓真的该死
Those god damned thugs!
人家看病的钱也抢走
Stealing people's medical fees!
市面不好，才会有贼
It's the economy. People turn to crime.
陈伯，那我们怎么办呢？
Uncle Chan, what shall we do?
怎么样…借到钱没有？
Did you manage to borrow money?
我问过了，住医院要三个大头
I asked. The hospital fee is $3.
三个大头
Three dollars!
金医生，她借来的钱给人抢走了
Dr Kim, she's just been robbed!
那怎么办，不进医院要死的
He'll die if he doesn't go to the hospital!
妈
Ma...
孩子，你明知爸爸妈妈没钱
Son, you know we don't have money.
为什么要病呀！
Why did you have to fall sick?
事情也太不巧了
It's such an unlucky coincidence!
我把钱都买了肥皂了
I spent all my money on soap.
我也是，钱都买了面粉
Me too. I spent mine on flour.
要不然…
Otherwise...
妈
Ma...
福哥，我这儿一块大头
Brother Fook, here's a dollar.
你先拿去吧，我不买被子了
Take it. I'm not buying a blanket.
我今天刚刚赚了一个大头
I just made a dollar today.
你先拿去吧！
You take it first.
现在还差一块钱，谁有，谁还有
We're still a dollar short. Who has it?
福哥，这个大头是我老婆的嫁妆
Ah Fook, this dollar is my wife's dowry.
本来是准备留给我女儿的
I was keeping it for my daughter,
可惜女儿打仗时候被炸死了
but she was killed in the war.
现在没有用了
I've no use for it now.
你拿去给孩子看病吧！
Use it for your son's treatment.
多谢陈伯
Thank you, Uncle Chan.
好了，好了，别多说了
All right, all right, no more words.
赶快进医院，走
Let's get him to the hospital.
让我来，来，乖！
I'm coming. Come on. Good boy.
小心点
Careful.
快，快！
Quick, quick!
快点吧！
Hurry up!
这年头，没钱千万别生病啊！
Nowadays, you can't get sick if you're poor.
就是嘛，我先下去看看煮的粥了
How true! I'll see if the congee's ready.
我们也该去洗衣服了
We should go wash some clothes.
发仔哥，你的衣服怎么破了
Fat Chai, why is your jacket torn?
一定是刚才
It must have got ripped just now
又忙又乱的时候勾破的
in all the commotion.
趁我妈还没回来，快点脱下来
My mum's not back yet. Take it off
我给你补一补吧！
and I'll mend it for you.
谢谢你
Thank you.
拿来吧！     谢谢！
Give it to me. -Thank you!
对了，我搬来没几天
I've only been here a few days
整天看你挨打
but I see your mother beat you all the time.
你妈怎么那么凶啊！
Why is she so cruel?
我不是她亲生的
I'm not her real daughter.
我九岁的时候，她就把我买过来
She bought me when I was 9 years old.
怪不得！
No wonder!
我跟你差不多
I'm a bit like you.
我从小就没了父母了
I also lost my parents when I was little.
发仔哥
Fat Chai,
你是不是读过很多的书啊？
have you studied a lot?
那有钱读书
Who has the money to go to school?
我十二岁就学补鞋了
I started mending shoes when I was 1 2.
那么你怎么那么能干？
Then how come you're so capable?
什么能干？
Capable? How so?
比如你敢跟太子炳作对
Like when you opposed Master Bing,
又肯帮助同屋住户
and the way you help your neighbors.
我不知该怎么说
I don't know how to say it,
总而言之，你实在太好了
but well, you're just too good.
其实也没什么
There's nothing on it, really.
一个人只要走正路
As long as a man walks a straight path
吃点亏也不在乎的话，准没错
and doesn't mind taking a few knocks,
这不就是能干吗？
he can't go wrong. Is that capable?
不，你会补衣服，我就不会
No. You can mend clothes and I can't,
你不比我能干？
so you're more capable than I am!
我不跟你说了
I'm not talking to you anymore.
发仔，发仔呀！
Fat Chai! Fat Chai!
我在这儿
I'm up here!
你怎么跑那儿去？
What are you doing up there?
阿香在给我补衣服
Ah Heung's mending my jacket.
补好了     谢谢你
All done. -Thank you!
来，你先吃这碗粥吧！
Come have some congee.
阿香在这儿正好
Ah Heung, you're here too. Good.
我知道八姑不回来是不许煮饭的
I know you can't eat until Pat Koo's back,
我想你肚子一定很饿的
so you must be very hungry.
你先吃碗粥吧！
Here, have some congee first.
不要了，你们两个吃吧！
No thanks. You two have it.
我们一人少吃一口
We'll just each have a little less.
阿香，阿香，真他妈倒霉
Ah Heung! Ah Heung! What rotten luck!
八圈牌输了十六底
I lost 16 games in 8 rounds of mahjong.
阿香，开门      来了
Ah Heung, open the door. -Coming!
倒茶
Pour me some tea.
真倒霉
Dammit! What rotten luck!
妈
Ma.
你看你这死相
Look at your damned face!
我看你就有气
It makes me angry just looking at you.
都是你呀
It's all your fault!
跑到那处，叫我一声妈
Calling me Ma everywhere.
害我八圈牌输了十六底
Making me lse 16 games in 8 rounds!
站着干什么？
What are you standing there for?
你明知我打牌累
You know very well I've been playing mahjong.
还不跟我捶捶
Give a massage already!
用点力行不行？
Put a little strength into it.
你没吃饭哪！
Haven't you eaten?
我是没吃饭啊！
No, I haven't.
早上不是有半碗冷饭吗？
Wasn't there half a bowl of leftovers?
只有半碗冷饭，我吃了还不够饱
Half a bowl wasn't filing enough.
你去死了吧！
Damn you!
你疯了，你吃那么多
Have you gone crazy?
你想把我吃穷了
You want to eat me out of house and home?
楼上静点行不行啊！
Can you keep quiet upstairs?
你想清静
If you want peace and quiet,
想清静有地方
there's a perfect place for it:
你为什么不搬到殡仪馆去住！
why don't you go live in a mortuary?
好多沙子啊，我们在喝粥呢
You're making dust fall. We're having congee!
喝粥有什么了不起
You're having congee? So what?
要是你们吃全席的话那还得了
It's not as if you're having a full banquet!
我要理     八婆！
Answer me! -Bitch!
老虎不发威把我当病猫？
What makes you think you can pick on me?
我愿意，我高兴
I just happen to like it noisy.
发仔，你干什么？
Fat Chai, what are you doing?
你干什么？
What are you doing?
你要拆房子啊
You want to tear the house down?
发仔
Fat Chai!
杨伯别管我
Let me be, Uncle Yeung.
救命呀！有人要拆房子啊
Help! Someone's tearing down the house!
你个死小子
You damned kid!
发仔
Fat Chai!
你以为我怕你呀
You think I'm scared of you?
我怕你是不是
You think I'm scared, is that it?
发仔
Fat Chai!
我看你把我怎么样？
What are you going to do?
你怎么打人呀？
Why are you hitting people?
杨伯，拿把刀来
Uncle Yeung, hand me a knife.
剁来做白云猪蹄子
I'll cut me some pig's trotters!
发仔
Fat Chai!
你骂够了没有
You dare insult me!
对不起，对不起
Sorry, sorry!
你这个死小子，我跟你拼了
You damned kid, I'll show you!
杨伯，别拉我
Let's see what she'll do.
什么事这么吵？
What's all this racket?
你回来得正好
You've come back just in time.
刚才那死小子想拆我们的楼
That bloody kid tried to tear the house down.
弄坏了楼板
Smashed up the floorboards.
在哪儿？
Where?
就在这儿
Right here.
我的肚子，刚才那个王八蛋
It hurts! Just now that bastard
把我气得上气不接下气
made me so mad I couldn't breathe.
堵住了中气，痛死我了！
Now my chest hurts! Oh, the agony!
老八，你不要生气了
Don't be so angry.
有气你留给我受
Just leave it to me.
你自己何必这么辛苦呢？
Why trouble yourself so?
要不然到隔壁弄两口抽抽
Go next door and have a smoke.
顺顺气好不好，我亲爱的老八
Calm yourself down, my dear.
你说得对
You're right.
死丫头，把钱包拿过来
Get me the purse, you damned girl!
快点，快点
Hurry up! Hurry up!
快点，快点     妈
Hurry up! Hurry up! -Yes, Ma.
可怜了
Poor thing.
你这个色鬼，等我回来再睡
Wait for me, you sex fiend!
知道了，老佛爷
Yes, Your Majesty.
我每天晚上没有你的话
Don't I wait for you every night?
怎么能够睡得着
How can I sleep without you?
你等我呀
Wait for me.
小心点，慢慢走！
Watch your step. Go slow.
你干什么嘛炳叔？
What are you doing, Uncle Bing?
这有什么关系呀
What does it matter?
过来让我亲亲你
Just let me give you a little kiss.
炳叔，你别走过来，不要…
Uncle, don't come any closer! No!
这有什么不好
What's the big deal?
其实我每天晚上都在想着你
Actually I think of you every night,
不过那个老八老看着我
but what can I do with the missus around?
我没有办法，看你嫩皮白肉
Look at you, so young and fresh;
那个老八她怎能跟你比呀
how can that old trout compare with you?
过来让我亲亲
Come. Give me a kiss.
不要，不要，你让开
No! Leave me alone!
没关系嘛
What's the big deal?
你不要这样，炳叔你别过来
No! Uncle, don't come any closer
不要
No! No!
这有什么关系
What is it!
炳叔，你别过来
Uncle Bing, don't come any closer!
你过来我就喊救命
If you do, I'll scream!
不要
No, don't!
救命啊
Help!
着火啦，着火啦
Fire, fire!
大家快来救火啊！
Fire! Put out the fire!
快点打电话吧！
Call the fire brigade!
救火啊，救火啊
Fire! Fire!
阿香，没事吧？     没事
Ah Heung, are you all right? -Yes, I'm OK.
着火啦，着火啦
Fire!, Fire!
五叔，五叔
Uncle Hu! Uncle Hu!
不好了，着火啊
Fire! Put out the fire!
快救火啊
Put out the fire!
什么事呀？
What's the matter?
着火了
Fire!
你的铃呢！     铃都掉了
Where's your bell? -I lost it.
快跑呀！
Run!
着火了，快救火啊
Fire! Help put out the fire!
快救火啊
Help put out the fire!
发仔，哪儿着火了？
Fat Chai, where's the fire?
我也不知道，我正在干活
I don't know. I was working,
听楼上阿香喊救命
then I heard Ah Heung cry for help,
我以为着火呢！
so I thought there was a fire.
你这死发仔，我楼上哪儿着火了
Damned kid! Where the hell's the fire?
不着火，阿香喊救命干什么？
If there's no fire, why did she cry for help?
你说，说，阿香你说
Ah Hsiang, you tell me.
我…
I...
怕什么，这么多人
Don't be afraid. There's so many people here.
我告诉你，阿香
I'm warning you, Ah Heung,
你要敢说一句
if you dare say a word,
等你妈回来就打死你
I'll have your Ma beat you to death.
我没…
I...didn't...
你再说，你敢说
You wouldn't dare.
还不跟我回去
Come home with me.
没事了，大家回去了
All right, show's over, break it up.
救火车来了
The firemen are here.
让开，让开
Make way! Make way!
走开，走开
Move back! Move back!
救火呀，走开
Fire! Move back!
跟我来，跟我来
Follow me! Follow me!
在前面，跟我来
Right over here. Follow me!
这儿才是九十六号嘛
Here's No. 96!
来，走，走
Come on.
慢着，外边你可看好
Wait. You keep watch out here.
走
Go!
谁是房东？
Who's the landlord?
我是，我就是
That's me, that's me.
原来是你呀，大黑痣
So it's you, Big Mole.
什么事？     听着
What's going on? -Listen.
里边可以放水了吗？
Can we turn the tap on now?
慢等，正在谈呢？
Wait. We're still negotiating.
听着
Listen.
有钱有水，没钱没水
Cash equals splash, no cash no splash.
要水给钱，没钱没水
You pay we spray, no pay no stay.
对不起，你们再说清楚点好不好
Sorry, could you explain that again please?
你真是麻烦，听清楚点
What a nuisance. Listen carefully.
听着，听着
Listen.
有钱有水，没钱没水
Cash equals splash, no cash no splash.
要水给钱，没钱没水
You pay we spray, no pay no stay.
你们要钱是不是
You're asking for money?
当然了，没有钱有什么好谈的
Of course, no money, no talk.
别啰啰嗦苏的，快点呀
You'd better make up your mind quickly.
要不然我们就不管了
The pipe might get blocked any minute.
哥儿们，你们全弄错了
Brothers, you've made a mistake.
这个地方根本没有着火
There's no fire here!
没着火！
No fire?
太不像话     就是
Preposterous! -You said it.
你骗我们
Are you having us on?
没着火就叫我们来
Why call us if there's no fire?
是谁打电话？
Who made the call?
打电话的是我，喊着火的是他
I did, but he's the one who yelled "fire".
你的罪过可大了
This is a serious transgression.
过来
Quick, quick.
叫什么名，干什么的？
Name and profession?
我叫发仔，补鞋的
My name's Fat Chai. I'm a cobbler.
补鞋的
A cobbler?
小曾，补鞋的没有钱的
Cheng, cobblers don't have money.
我知道了，大黑痣过来
I know. Big mole, come here.
我们现在新规定
According to our new regulations,
叫着火的无罪
the one who yells fire gets off,
打电话的要负全责
but whoever calls it in is responsible.
还有我们一到了现场
Also, once we're at the scene,
就照样要放水兼拆房子
we must hose the house and demolish it.
拆房子？
Demolish the house?
因为我们怕有炉子什么碰倒了
In case a stove or something turns over
容易引起真的火灾来
and causes a real fire.
没错，拆房子
Right. Level the house!
不要拆房子啊！
No, don't!
有话慢慢说嘛
Iet's talk this over.
兄弟啊，美人说句话就是不同
Thus speaketh the beauty, lads.
大黑痣，你该知道了
Big Mole, you know the score.
兄弟，那你开个价吧
You name a price.
起码一条黄金
At the very least, one gold bar.
你说什么，一条黄金
What? One gold bar?
就这个破房子
For this delapidated house?
破房子，破房子就是危楼
A delapidated house is dangerous.
拆     不能拆
Level it. -No!
老八，这几个死小子很难对付
These guys are hard to handle.
我看你不拿点钱出来很难办了
I think you had better pay them off.
怎么办？
What should we do?
这是什么？
What's this?
干什么？
Why are you taking my bracelet?
喝杯茶
Treat yourself to a drink.
这是真的，不假的
This is genuine, is it not?
这是真金吧？
Real gold?
那还错得了吗？
Of course!
不只，还有
We need more than that.
这就当给我点面子吧！
Come on, give me a bit of face.
给点面子
行，这个还给你
All right. This is yours.
够意思   这个是我的
Great. -This is mine.
够朋友
You're a pal.
大黑痣，你住哪儿？
Big Mole, which flat is yours?
上面，最漂亮那间
The nicest one, up there.
就在上面
That one up there.
请上去喝杯茶…
Come up and have some tea.
等等，兄弟，上面最漂亮那间
In a while, lads. The nicest one up there.
你明白了吗？
Understood?
弟兄们，拆最漂亮那间
Level the nicest one, lads.
是
Yes sir!
不能拆，不能拆
No! No!
我给你，我全部都给你，给你…
I'll give you everything! Everything!
阿炳，你还有一个挂表
Ah Bing, you still have a pocket watch.
全都给了他们
Give them everything!
没有
There's nothing,
这个没什么的
there's really nothing.
你干什么呢？
What are you doing?
我们来的多，每个人只能分一点
There's not enough to go round so many of us.
拆好了没有？
Are you finished in there?
钱到了，走人
We got the money. Let's go.
记着，以后要是真的着火
Remember, if ever you have a real fire,
最要紧的是打电话找我
be sure to call us.
再见
Bye!
你们这些绝子绝孙的
You god damn bastards!
你们这样做还不如去抢
They're no better than robbers.
买了，买了，买了就有
Come on, place your bets.
买了，买了
开！
Open!
森哥，换班了
Brother Shum, we've just changed shifts.
这么快你就下班啦？
Off work so soon?
快就快了点
Yes, it is a bit soon.
虽然这条街是你地方
This is your street.
我少来
I'm not here often.
你在这儿等我
Wait for me here.
买了，买了就有
Place your bets.
钟哥，三六九来了在那边
Brother Chung, 369 is over there.
妈的，拿点钱给他花吧
Damn! Give him some money.
胖子，拿那衣服来
Fatso, hand me my jacket.
这儿就交给你了
I'm leaving you in charge.
好，你放心吧
Don't worry, leave it to me.
买，买
Place your bets!
开，开
Opening up!
买，买
Place your bets!
买定离手
Hands off the table!
三六九   怎么这么少？
369 -ls that all?
今天生意不好吗
Yes, business is bad tonight.
不好
Bad?
刚才开完一二，买三吧！
It was 1 and 2 just now. Try 3!
我偏不买三，我买四
Not 3. I'll bet on 4.
阿朱，买四
Ah Chu, I'm betting on 4.
好的，好小子
Very well, kid.
三六九，你买四
369. Your betting on 4.
开，摊开三
There it is. Three!
三六九，我找你好半天了
369, I've been looking for you all day!
你到哪儿去了？
Where have you been?
炳哥，什么事啊？
What's the matter, Brother Bing?
我告诉你
I'm telling you,
昨天晚上丢了很多金条
I lost a lot of gold bars last night.
谁那么大胆敢偷你的东西？
Who'd dare steal from you?
别说这么多了，我慢慢再告诉你
I'll tell you the details later.
你听着，明天你到都顺街
Listen, go to To Shun Street tomorrow,
九十六号陈园那里
Look for no. 96, Chan Yuen.
陈园？我没去过
Chan Yuen? I've never been there.
没有去过，你去找嘛
That's why you need to look for it.
你记着
Remember. Once you're there,
一到那儿就抓那个补鞋的发仔
arrest Fat Chai, the cobbler.
一、二、三
One, two, three.
一、二
One, two.
一、二、一、二…
One, two, one two.
四妹，拿口袋去买米了
Fourth sister, let's go buy some rice.
我先去拿钱
I'll go get the money.
发仔哥，你要不要买点东西？
Fat Chai, is there anything you need?
不要买什么了，谢谢福嫂
Nothing, thanks, Mrs Fook.
好，我们走吧
OK. Let's go
发仔哥，我们走了
See you later, Fat Chai.
再见！  再见！
Bye! -Bye!
发仔哥，发仔哥，这回我完了
Fat Chai! I'm really in trouble this time!
什么事？
What's wrong?
就在着火那天晚上
Ma found out what happened
我妈知道了炳叔的事
with Uncle Bing on the night of the fire.
他们两大吵了一场
They had a huge argument
现在还要把我卖到导游社
and now they want to sell me
做导游女
to a travel agency to be a tour guide.
什么话
What?
那种地方你也能去
How can they send you to such a place?
那不等于妓女吗？
That's just like becoming a prostitute!
所以呀，发仔哥
Fat Chai, you must help me this time!
这回你要救救我
这怎么办？
What shall I do now?
不如这样吧
Let's do this. Go straight to the police station
你马上去分局，告他们迫良为娼
and say they're forcing you into prostitution.
九十六号陈园，没错
No. 96, Chan Yuen. This is it.
刚好巡警来
Perfect! Here comes a policeman.
兄弟，这儿是不是有个叫…
Pal, is there someone here called...
巡警先生
Mr Policeman,
这位大姑娘正要找你有事
this young lady needs to talk to you.
会有这么漂亮的大姑娘要找我
Such a pretty young lady wants to talk to me?
有什么事？你哭了？
What's the matter? You're crying?
有什么事情？你说
Tell me what the matter is.
我…   说啊
I... -Well?
我知道了，你这小子一定是姓楚
I know. It's you, isn't it?
楚完溜，是不是？
You humped her and dumped her, right?
你别在胡说
Shut your big mouth!
我胡说
My big mouth?
我一看见你就知道你不是好人
I knew you were no good the moment I saw you.
大姑娘，你不用怕
Don't be afraid, young lady.
有什么事情你尽管说好了
Whatever it is, you can tell me.
只要医生证明你破了
Once a doctor proves you've been deflowered,
我马上就会抓他
I'll arrest him immediately!
你不要瞎猫捉死耗子好不好
Don't jump to crazy conclusions!
这件事不关我的事
It's got nothing to do with me.
不关你的事难道还关我的事？
Nothing to do with you?
这种事情还能两个人一块来吗？
So who did it? Me?
这件事她妈…
It's her mother...
你还在骂人？
Now you're trying to blame her mother?
不干不净的他妈他妈的
Why drag her mother into this?
我妈可没有得罪你？
What did her mother ever do to you?
我是说这件事
What I'm trying to say is,
是她妈逼她去做生意
her mother's forcing her into "business".
怎么说你就不对了
What's wrong with that?
大姑娘，你自己想一想
Think about it, young lady.
做生意吗要赚钱
Going into business means making money.
有钱你都不肯赚，你今年几岁？
Don't you want money? How old are you?
十九岁
Nineteen.
十九岁还小？
19. You're not a kid anymore!
我十六岁就接生意了
I started doing business when I was 16.
你知不知道她妈叫她做什么生意
Do you know what kind of business?
做什么生意？
What kind of business?
做导游女
To be a so-called "tour guide".
导游女，那不就是妓女？
Tour guide? That's being a prostitute!
就是了
Isn't that so!
十九岁就做妓女，不是小一点
A 19-year-old prostitute's a bit young.
那你又说你十六岁就出来接客
You said you started yourself at 1 6.
我那是做那种生意的？
I didn't mean that kind of business!
怎么？
What business was it?
我是接火柴盒回家里去做的
I made matchboxes at home.
那有那样的母亲逼女儿去做妓女
What mother forces her kid to be a whore?
她母亲呢？
Where's her mother?
她不是她亲生的母亲
She's not her real mother.
她是买回来的
She bought her.
怪不得呢？她有罪啊！
No wonder! That makes her guilty.
你可以告她逼良为娼
You can charge her.
发仔哥
Fat Chai, is that true?
是不是真的？
Fat hai, is that true?
当然是真的了，骗你是王八蛋
Sure! I wouldn't lie to you.
告诉我，我马上去把她抓回来
Tell me where I can arrest her.
阿香，这就不用怕了
Ah Heung, you don't have to be scared now.
想不到巡警里头
I never thought there'd be such a good man
也会有你这种大好人
among the ranks of you policemen.
其实你们一看见我
From the moment you saw me
就应该知道我三六九是个大好人
you should have known 369 is a great guy.
还有那些聋子、哑吧、瞎子
Those deaf, mute and blind people people
都以为我是包公再世呢
all think I'm Justice incarnate!
好了，不要再说了
All right, no more chit-chat.
快去抓他妈去吧     行
go arrest her mother. -Righto.
慢着
Hold it. I didn't come here for this.
我到这儿来不是为这件事的
我为什么事呢？
What did I come here for?
是不是来抓人？
Did you come to arrest someone?
没错，抓人
That's right, to arrest someone.
抓谁呢？
Arrest who?
抓谁呢？我抓谁呢？
Arrest who? Who am I arresting?
阿香，你这死丫头原来躲在这儿
Ah Heung! So there you are, you damned girl!
这就是她妈！
That's her mother!
我知道了，你听着
Got it. Listen, you.
死八婆
You old witch!
听说你要把女儿卖给导游社
You're selling your daughter to an agency.
这就是逼良为娼
That's forcing her into prostitution.
你有罪，跟我到警察局去
That's a criminal ofence. Come with me.
我把她从小买了回来养到这么大
I bought her when she was a child.
我花了多少钱
I spent a lot of money raising her.
我现在把她卖给别人
So now I'm selling her on to someone else.
没什么不对
What's so wrong with that?
你这个臭娘们，你那么想钱
What a bitch! If you want money,
为什么不自己去卖
why don't you go sell yourself?
你看你那副德性
Look at you!
长得歪里歪斜，八歪八扭的
What a crooked-looking face!
我一看你就知道你不是个好人
I knew you were no good the moment I saw you.
你看看我们长得多帅，多自然
Look at how nice we look, how natural.
你只要仔细一看
If you look closely,
就知道我们三个
you'll see that all three of us
是道道地地的正人君子
are regualr, authentic good people!
看够了没有
Seen enough?
走，跟我到警察局去
Come with me to the station!
你这个混蛋在这儿干什么？
You idiot! What're you standing there for?
太子炳怎么你这么巧也在这儿
Master Bing, what a coincidence!
我…
I...
我找到一条财路
I've discovered a way to make money.
什么财路？
What way?
有个八婆想逼良为娼
Someone's forcing girls into prostitution.
那你得多要点了
Then you must put the squeeze on her.
当然了，这还用你教吗？
Of course! I know what to do.
那个八婆在哪儿？
Where's this no-good bitch?
你这个该死的
You god damned bastard!
你眼睛瞎了，她是我老婆
Are you blind? That's my wife!
太子炳，你不用骗我
Master Bing, what a kidder you are!
你老婆肥婆四我认识
I know who your wife is. Fat Woman Sei!
死一边去
Go to hell!
阿炳，谁个肥婆四？
Ah Bing, who's Fat Woman Sei?
没事，你这该死的，叫嫂子呀
Nothing. You idiot, say hello to my wife!
这个也是嫂子？
This one's your wife too?
什么？
What?
没事，没事
Nothing, nothing.
快叫呀
Greet her, quick.
阿嫂
Ma'am.
你这个该死的东西
You stupid fool!
我叫你来抓发仔
I told you to arrest Fat Chai!
你抓我老婆干什么？
What are you doing arresting my wife?
对了，我明明是进来抓补鞋仔的
That's right. I came to arrest the cobbler.
发仔在哪儿？
Where's Fat Chai?
他不就是啦！
That's him right there.
那个就是呀！
That's him.
不就是他吗！
That's him?
你听着，我先上楼上去
Listen, I'm going up.
这件事情交给你办     好
You sort things out here. -OK!
回去，回去，你这个死丫头
Come with me, you damned girl!
快抓她，快抓她
Arrest her! Quick, arrest her!
我现在要抓你
You're under arrest.
阿炳，快实说，谁是肥婆四
Ah Bing, the truth. Who's Fat Woman Sei?
你干什么？
What are you doing?
无缘无故你抓我干什么？
Why are you arresting me for no reason?
什么无缘无故
For no reason?
我本来就是来抓你的
You're the reason I came in the first place!
我一进门就看你小子不顺眼
As soon as I stepped through the door,
我就知道你不是个好人
I knew you were no good.
这就不对了
That's not right.
你刚才不是说我是个大好人吗
Didn't you say I was a good guy just now?
刚才是刚才的事
That was then, this is now.
去年很多有钱的人
There were lots of rich people last year too
今天不也变成大闸蟹
who've all gone bankrupt this year!
多少岁？说！
Age? Speak!
什么事？
What's going on?
抽壮丁
It's the draft!
多少岁，快说
What's your age? Quick!
二十四岁
Twenty-four.
正好，中选
Excellent. You're drafted.
有没有弄错，什么岁数也中选
What? Just on account of my age?
凡是十八岁到四十岁
Any able-bodied male between 1 8 and 24
都是壮丁年龄
你正好就中选了
is elible for the draft.
跟我到警察局去
Come with me to the station.
动手动脚的，干什么？
Hey, hands off!
有话的慢慢的谈吗
Let's discuss this.
其实我进来一眼看见你
The moment I laid eyes on you
就知道你这个人很聪明
I knew you were a smart person.
你要跟我谈一谈，是不是？
You want to discuss things, right?
干什么？这什么意思？
What do you mean?
公价人情，五斗米
Standard price. Five pecks of rice.
你发神经啊？
Have you gone mad?
夏季大减价，三斗好了
Summer discount. Three pecks.
你给我？
You're giving it to me?
就这么说吧
Let's say...
你给我三块大头好了
you give me 3 HK dollars.
也没有，我有一条命你要不要？
I don't have it either. Just take my life!
你这个小子脾气这么硬呀
What a stubborn kid you are!
干干脆脆给我一块大头好了
Just give me a dollar then.
去你妈的，没有
Up yours! I don't have it.
好货
Very well then.
你干什么，抢东西
What're you doing? This is robbery!
代罚款，代罚款
It's just a token fine.
什么代罚款，简直是抢劫
What token fine? It's daylight robbery!
我三六九还要抢，你真是混帐
I'm a cop, I don't have to rob. Idiot!
发仔，什么事？什么事？
What's wrong, Fat Chai?
金医生，他抢我东西
Dr Kim, he's robbing me!
他是巡警，怎么会抢东西呢
He's a cop, how can he be robbing you?
他比贼还坏
He's worse than a common thief!
哎…你说什么？
What are you saying?
你是不是医生？    是啊！
Are you a doctor? -Yes.
医什么的？
What do you specialise in?
内科、外科、妇科、牙科
Gynaecology, surgery, dentistry...
牙科，正好，我这儿有个坏牙
Dentistry? Geat! I've got a rotten tooth.
帮我拔掉，走…
Take it out for me, will you?
哎呀，我不会拔牙啊！
I don't know how to pull teeth!
你这该死的，牙科医生不会拔牙
What kind of dentist doesn't pull teeth?
你看见我穿这身老虎皮
Is it because of my uniform?
怕我不给钱是不是
You think I won't pay. Is that it?
说了半天，这才是良心话
That's the first true thing you said all day.
你少废话
Shut up.
老不死的，你是不见棺材不掉泪
You're asking for it, you old fool.
今年多少岁？
How old are you?
五十岁，干什么？
Fifty. Why?
十八，四十，你有没有牌？
18 to 40. Have you got a license?
我从山东刚到这儿来
I just arrived from Shantung.
那来的牌？
Where would I get a licence from?
那你为什么不去领牌？
Why didn't you apply for one?
我是想去领的
I was intending to,
可是又要担保，又要证书
but they need guarantees, certificates,
又要人事，九十几重手续
connections, and dozens of forms filled.
单在你们牌照部
At the licensing department alone
就被你们的弟兄骂了一百零八次
I got told off God knows how many times!
你自己找来骂吗！
You brought it on yourself.
衙门里的规矩你都不懂
You should know how officialdom operates.
好了，不用多说了，走吧
OK, no more talk. Let's go!
没有牌跟我回警察局去
No licence? Back to the station with me!
老兄，帮帮忙行不行？
Please, could you do me a favour this once?
你这个老不死的
You old fool.
我都说你是不见棺材不掉泪
I told you you were asking for it.
你想我不抓你吗？行
You want me to let you go? Sure.
你给我把牙拔掉
Pull my tooth for me.
好，我拔，我拔，可是没有家伙
OK, I'll do it. But I need some tools.
起码得有把钳子
At the very least, a pair of pincers.
钳子？
Pincers?
你又偷东西呀？
You're stealing again?
慢着慢着
Wait a minute.
把你的东西借用一下
I'm just borrowing your stuff for a moment.
你想我会偷你的钱
You think I'd steal your money?
神经病的
You're crazy!
你才神经病
You are the one who's crazy!
老兄，帮帮忙
Brother, do me a favour.
我的鞋跟松了，给我钉一钉
The heel's come loose. Fix it, would you?
钱呢？
Where's the money?
大家都是兄弟不用算了
Come on, we're brothers!
谁跟你做兄弟？
Who's your brother?
这就叫协助警方，钉紧一点
It's called assisting the police. Fix it!
神经病
Crazy fool!
钳子
There, pincers.
老虎钳，老虎钳怎么行啊！
They're too big. How can I use it?
什么不成？
Why not?
想让我抓你回警察局，是不是？
Do you want me to arrest you?
好，我拔，你坐…坐
OK, OK. Sit down.
你干什么？
What are you doing?
我的力气不够
I haven't got the strength.
踩开点
Bend a little.
哪一颗啊？
Which one?
下边…
Down there.
你的嘴怎么那么臭啊
Your breath really stinks!
你是不是不刷牙！
Don't you brush your teeth?
到底是哪一颗？
Which one?
这个…
This one...
哪一颗？
Which one is it?
这个…
This one...
老不死的，到底有没有拔呀！
Have you pulled it yet, old fool?
拔了！你看，牙不是在这儿
I've pulled it. Look, here it is.
你这老不死，你拔错了
You idiot! You pulled the wrong one!
下边那个才是，你拔了上边那个
It's the one below. You pulled the one on top!
下边的烂牙还在这儿
The rotten one's still there!
这不便宜了你，三六九
You got yourself a bargain, 369!
你爱贪小便宜
You like bargains, don't you?
这样买一送一很花得来啊！
Buy one, get one free!
是呀，反正不用钱
That's right, it's free anyway.
拔两只也没关系
One tooth or two, it doesn't matter.
你不如把满嘴牙都拔了
Why don't you have them all pulled?
鞋修好了，怎么样
I've fixed your shoe. How's that?
放在这儿
Leave it here.
金医生，来
Come on, Dr Kim.
我没有力气了
I've got no strength left.
发仔，帮帮忙     好好
Give me a hand, Fat Chai. -Sure.
你要了我的命，你大概做惯了强盗
You want to kill me? What are you,
是不是？
a bandit or something?
搂住这儿…
Hold tight here.
金娇、银娇、紫罗莲
Gold, Silver, Violet!
快点出来见客，快点呀
Come quickly and greet our guests!
来了
Coming!
你们快点！
Hurry up!
客人来了好半天了，走
They've been waiting a long time.
二少，二少，姑娘们都来了
Sir, the girls are here.
快进来
Come in quickly.
二少，还要什么人侍候请快点说
Sir, if you want anyone else, just say so.
不用了，待一会儿我再要你
That's all right. Maybe I'll have you later.
你真混蛋，去吧，去吧
You rotter! Go on.
老板娘   来了
Boss lady! -Coming.
有什么事，快点说
What's the matter? Out with it quick.
三六九来了
369 is here.
三六九，你怎么也中毒了？
369, have you been poisoned?
钉
Nail!
搞得生疔啊？
You have a wart?
你到底有什么事情，快点说
What's the matter? Be quick with it.
钉你个死人头
Nail your ass!
是钉棺材盖的钉子
This is a coffin nail!
我说你们老板？
Where's your boss?
跟八姑在聊天呢？
He's chatting with Pat Koo.
你说什么？
What did you say?
我们那个破屋子值八条黄金？
Our run-down house is worth 8 bars?
不过我们要空房子
But we want vacant possession.
因为我们要装修好才能开张的吗
We'll have to rennovate the place.
阿炳啊！你听见了没有？
Ah Bing, did you hear that?
我们那破屋子可以值八条黄金啊
Our old house is worth 8 gold bars?
听见了，你以为我是聋子
I heard you. You think I'm deaf?
峰哥，你怎能开这么多导游社
How come you have so many travel agencies,
奉旨的？
Brother Feng? It's as if by imperial decree!
不是奉旨的
It's not imperial decree.
不过她的干爹是分局的局长
Her godfather's the police chief, though.
你这个傻瓜
You stupid fool!
逢年过节，我要送很多礼的
At festive times, we give a lot of gifts.
怪不得呢，不过如果查了出来
No wonder! But if he's found out,
她的干爹不是有麻烦吗？
won't he get into a lot of trouble?
这怕什么，最多买张飞机票
What's to worry? He can always buy a ticket
一飞就飞走了
and just fly away from it all.
不什么事都没有了吗？
What trouble will there be then?
走开，走开，让我来问他
Make way. I want to ask him something.
我们那屋子真的值八条黄金吗？
Is our house really worth 8 gold bars?
当然了，宝贝
Of course, darling.
老八，我们先把谁赶走？
So who shall we get rid of first?
那还用问
Do you have to ask?
当然是那个卖香烟的杨伯了
Uncle Yeung the cigarette vendor, of course.
八姑，我谢谢你
Pat Koo, I'll thank you
你不能扔我的东西了
not to throw away my things.
八姑，你做做好事，我求求你
Pat Koo, I beg you, have pity!
你叫我以后怎么生活呢？八姑
How will I live if you turn me out?
杨伯，杨伯，你不要着急呀
Uncle Yeung, don't worry.
你叫我以后怎么生活呢？
How will I live.
什么事呀？
What's going on?
八姑，你干什么？
Pat Koo, what are you doing?
干什么，我要他搬家
What do you think? I'm evicting him.
要我搬家
She wants me to move out!
别动手，什么事？
Hold it! What's going on?
她要赶杨伯走
She's evicting Uncle Yang.
你为什么赶杨伯走？
Why do you want to get rid of him?
他交不出房钱，我当然要他搬家
Of course I'm evicting him. He owes rent.
你当我这儿是什么？
What do you think this place is?
我这儿是善堂呀？
A charity home?
他一共欠你多少钱？
How much does he owe you?
欠得可多了，一个月十斤米
A lot! It's 10 catties of rice a month,
欠我六个月的房钱
and he owes me for 6 months.
就是六十斤米，按照市价
That's 60 catties. At the market price,
六七四十二，就是四十二万
6 x 7=42, that's 420,000.
就这么多啊？
That much?
是啊，你有没有？
Yes. Do you have it?
现在买两个砂锅要多少钱？
How much is it now to buy 2 pots?
大概十万块左右了
Around 1 00,000.
就算十万
Let's say 1 00,000 then.
还有这些杯子、碟子、匙羹
Plus all this crockery, cutlery
乱七八糟的就算十万吧
and other stuff, another 1 00,000.
用不了那么多，七万块钱就够了
Not that much. 70,000's enough.
好，就算七万
OK, 70,000.
杨伯，她打坏你香烟要弄多少钱
Uncle Yeung, how much for the cigarettes?
我的香烟大概四万块钱左右
My cigarettes? About 40 thousand.
四万，七万，十万
40,000, 70,000, 100,000.
一共是二十一万
That's 210,000 in total.
这个先拿着，算三个月的房租
You hold this. It's 3 month's rent.
其余的慢慢给你
You'll get the rest later.
你干什么？干什么？
What are you doing? What are you doing?
你有没有弄错你？
What the hell are you playing at?
当然没弄错了
I'm not playing at anythng.
怎么你打坏东西不赔？
Don't you have to pay for breaking things?
打坏了东西还用赔
If I had to pay,
要赔我就不打了
I wouldn't beak them in the first place.
打坏东西不用赔，是不是？
So you don't have to pay for breaking things?
当然不用赔了
Of course not!
好，大家听着
OK, listen everyone.
八姑说打坏东西不用赔
She says you can break things without paying!
那我们上楼把她的东西都打破了
Let's go upstairs and break all her stuff!
好呀
All right, all right!
好了，好了，我赔，我赔
I'll pay, I'll pay.
赔了…
死发仔我告诉你，这些算二十一万
Damn you, Fat Chai! That's 210,000,
但是他还欠我二十一万
but he still owes me another 210,000.
你今天无论如何要还给我
I must be paid today, no matter what.
要不然的话，说什么也没有用
Otherwise, there's nothing more to be said.
快点拿给我，拿来，二十一万
So give it to me. 210,000!
发仔，我这儿有两万
Fat Chai, I've got 20,000 here.
发仔，我这儿还有三万块
Fat Chai, I've got another 30,000.
好，三万
OK, 30,000.
我这儿有两万，拿去
I have 20,000 here, take it.
发仔，我这儿有一万五
Fat Chai, there's 15,000 here.
这是三万
Here's 30,000.
我这儿还有一万块钱
And here's 10,000.
还差六万
150,000. Still 60,000 short.
谁帮帮忙，还差六万
Can anyone help out? Another 60,000.
谁帮帮忙，差六万
你的药刚刚吃完了，医生说
You've just finished your medicine.
一定要买药回来吃才行啊！
The doctor says you need to get some more.
帮帮忙，还差六万块
Please help. We still need 60,000.
八姑，八姑，我老婆去收钱去了
Pat Koo, my wife's gone to collect money.
你再等两个钟头怎么样？
How about waiting another couple of hours?
就有六万块，你这个死人头
Who has 60,000, you dmaned idiot?
洗衣服能洗得了多少钱
How much can you make washing clothes?
你别在骗人了你
Don't try to con people.
够不够，不够给我滚
Is it enough? If not, out you go!
你们还有吗？
Have you got any?
没有了，你呢？   我也没有了
No? You? -I don't have any either.
我还是走了好
I suppose I'd better go.
不要再连累你们了
I don't want to trouble you anymore.
爷爷…
Gramps...
小福，爷爷赶明有空再回来看你
Little Fook, as long as Gramps is free,
乖乖的听妈的话
I'll come back to see you. Be good!
我要爷爷
I want Gramps!
杨伯
Uncle Yeung.
我走了
I'd better go.
杨伯，你先别走
Uncle Yeung, don't go.
杨伯，我这儿有六万块钱
Uncle Yeung, I've got 60,000 here.
你先拿去交租吧
use it to pay your rent.
不，韩先生
No, Mr Han.
我知道你这些钱是用来买药的
I know you need it for medicine.
你还是留着吧
Keep it for yourself.
杨伯，你把钱先拿去交租吧
Uncle Yeung, take it for your rent.
今天晚上我叫阿福到街上去借钱
I'll ask Ah fook to borrow some money tonight
还给韩先生
to pay back Mr Han.
对啊，杨伯，你先拿着吧
That's right, Uncle Yeung. You take it.
顶多我们再到别处借吧
We can always borrow some more later.
是呀
That's right.
对呀
杨伯，先拿着吧，拿着吧
Take it, Uncle Yeung.
谢谢…韩先生，谢谢…
Thank you, Mr. Han. Thank you.
不要客气，这个年头你不帮我
Don't mention it. How will we live
我不帮你，这日子怎么过？
if we don't help each other?
来，交给我
Here, give it to me.
八姑，这儿是二十一万
Pat Koo, here's 210,000.
那你自己数一数
You better count it.
我没空跟你数
I don't have time to count it for you.
我们帮杨伯把东西搬进去，来！
Let's help Uncle Yeung move back in.
真是谢谢大家，谢谢…
Thanks, everyone, Thank you so much!
八姑，这里也值二十一万的
Pat Koo, all this is worth 210,000 too.
记着拿回去，别再说钱不够
Don't forget it! Don't say it's not enough!
好了，我们走吧
OK, let's go.
没事了，走吧
Everything's fine, let's go.
好，我找三六九报复你这堕落鸡
I'll get 369 to sort you out, you whore!
你，过来！
You! Come here!
你先生姓韩
Isn't your husband's name Han Yi-Shi?
叫韩一世对不对？
对呀，什么事？
Yes. What's the matter?
韩一世
Han Yi-Shi.
有没有牌？查牌
You got a licence? I want to check.
查什么牌？
What license?
你以为我不知道，你是做舞女的
You think I don't know you're a hostess?
舞女时常兼做私娼
Hostesses usually moonlight as prostitutes,
私娼就是野鸡
and unlicensed prostitutes are against the law.
野鸡是犯法的，跟我到警察局
Come with me to the police station!
三六九，你动手动脚的干什么？
369, What are you doing here?
抓野鸡
Arresting an unlicensed whore.
你怎么知道她是野鸡？
How do you know she's a whore?
这还用问，你看她
Do you have to ask? Just look at her!
天黑的时候擦胭脂抹粉
All tarted up at this hour,
打扮得特别漂亮
wandering around the streets,
四处乱逛，还会是好人吗？
how could she be an honest woman?
你觉得她漂亮吗？不见得
You reckon she's pretty? I don't think so.
我觉得你老婆比她漂亮
I think your wife's prettier.
你认识我老婆？
You know my wife?
认识，挺风骚的     对…
Sure! She's real hot. -That's right!
你老婆也是天黑时候擦胭脂抹粉
Your wife dressed up in the evening too,
打扮得特别漂亮，四处乱逛
wandering around, looking great,
个子高高大大的，线条特别的…
She's tall, right? With great figure.
你老婆有牌吗？
Does your wife have a licence?
有我顶着还用领牌
She's got me, she doesn't need a licence.
有空来关照一下吧
Drop in to see us when you have time.
该死的
Dammit!
我怎么把这种丑事说出来
How could I have blurted this out!
三六九
369...
你老婆就是没有牌做野鸡
your wife's an unlicenced whore.
回去抓她吧
Go arrest her!
你这混账东西
You son of a bitch!
现在是我查她还是你查我？
Am I checking her or are you checking me?
走开
Get lost!
告诉我，你先生多大？
Tell me, how old's your husband?
什么事？
What for?
抽壮丁
The draft.
千万别抽他
Please don't pick him!
我先生有病，求求你帮帮忙吧
He's not well. Please!
好吧，那么还是老价钱吧
OK then. Same old price.
你…     五斗米
You... -5 pecks of rice.
我哪有五斗米？
Where would I get 5 pecks of rice?
你没有呀…
Do you have it or not?
夏季大减价三斗米
Summer discount, 3 pecks.
三斗也没有
I don't have 3 pecks either.
这样好吧
OK, let's do this.
大家都是朋友
We're all friends here.
给三块大头用用
I'll settle for 3 HK dollars.
我皮包里头那有这么多？
How would I have that much in my purse?
干干脆脆
Let's cut the bull. One dollar!
一块钱
原来你比我还熟
You're more familiar with this than I am!
我这份你干了算吧
Why don't you have my job?
赚到钱我们两人分
We'll split the money.
谁要干你这一行呀！
Who wants to do what yu do?
韩师母，不要怕
Don't be scared, Mrs Han.
这种人能欺负就欺负，能抢就抢
These people only prey on the weak.
不理他就没事，上班去吧
Just ignore him. Go to work.
谢谢福哥
Thanks, Brother Fook.
三六九，你别那么凶好不好
369, don't you go too far.
这个世界还有法律的
There are still laws in the world.
公道自在人心，你斗不过我们的
Justice is in men's hearts. You can't win!
又栽了…
Foiled again!
你真是没有用的，每次让你出马
You're useless!
没有一次是很顺利的
You never do anything right!
都是拖泥带水
Always messing things up!
又有什么办法
What can I do?
那个痨病鬼
Even that consumptive guy
连他自己看病的钱都拿了出来了
gave away his own medicine money.
三六九，每次叫你去对付人
Every time I ask you to sort someone out,
没有一次是痛痛快快的
you always make a mess of things!
一块钱两块钱你都要
You can't even pass up a buck or two!
大哥，一块两块也得抢才有啊
You won't get a buck if you pass it up!
是啊
Yeah!
你也不想想
You should stop to think:
现在要把楼上这帮穷人
if we get rid of these beggars upstairs,
统统都赶走
光这间屋子就值八条金子
the house alone will be worth 8 gold bars!
你不想一想
Try to imagine
我太子炳要有八条金子的话
if l, Master Bing, had 8 gold bars,
手指缝里漏一点给你
what benefits might trickle down to you!
你也不得了啊
你说这么多干什么了
Why all the words and no action then?
还不赶快想个办法
Hurry up and think of some way
把这帮穷鬼都赶出去
to get rid of this lot of beggars.
我已经想过了，说定了就这样办
I've thought it through.
这幢楼里边最恶的就是发仔
Fat Chai's the toughest of the lot.
先拿他开刀
We'll del with him first.
你说得对，有什么办法？
You're right, but how?
有什么办法？
But how?
你立刻去拿几件最漂亮的旗袍
Go wrap up a few of your best cheongsams
然后把它包起来，放在发仔那儿
and put them at Fat Chai's place.
然后呢，让三六九在门口等着
369, you wait outside.
等发仔一回来，你就大声嚷有贼
When Fat Chai returns, you yell "thief".
三六九上前一搜，人赃并获
369 will conduct a search, find the loot,
发仔被抓到警察局去
and haul him off to the police station.
你真聪明了，你应该发财
You're real smart. You deserve to get rich.
别讲那么多了，趁发仔还没回来
Enough talk. Hurry, before Fat Chai returns.
赶快拿进去，快点
Go put the things on his bunk, now!
我说炳哥，你想的计策真绝
I say, Brother Bing, that's real dastardly!
绝吧
Indeed!
你有儿子没有？
Do you have a son?
没有，干什么？
No. Why?
俗话说得好，要是缺德事做得多
They say that too many dastardly deeds
会绝子绝孙的
condemn one to having no pogeny.
去你妈的
Go to hell!
发仔哥
Fat Chai!
老八
Ah Bing.
快点
Hurry!
赶快拿进去，快点，快点
Put it in there quickly!
你去把风，我在那儿守着
You keep watch outside. I'll stay here
放好了？   放好了！
Done? -Done.
发仔回来了？     回来了
Finished work, Fat Chai? -Yes.
你现在上去，马上下来喊有贼
Go upstairs, then come down and yell "thief".
发仔，你收工？
Back from work, Fat Chai?
生意好吗？
How is business?
有贼呀，大家快点来呀…
Thief! Come quickly!
不得了，有贼…
不得了
Thief!
什么事？…
What's happening?
我刚才在楼上找东西
I was looking for something just now
我发现不见了一件红旗袍
and discovered I'm missing a red cheonsam,
一件绿旗袍，还有一件丝棉袄
a green one, as well as a padded silk jacket.
这三样东西可以值一担米呀
In all, they're worth 100 catties of rice!
我怎么办？
What am I going to do now?
别动，你们别动
Hold it, all of you!
你叫我怎么办？
What am I going to do?
别急，别急，急也没有用
Calm down. There's no use getting upset.
慢慢的说给大家听吗
Tell us exactly what happened.
来来来
Come, come.
说给大家听听
Tell everyone.
来来来，大家听听
Come, let's all hear it.
我一焦急就什么都说不出来
I'm so upset I can hardly speak.
大家听着，八姑又丢东西了
Listen, Pat Koo's lost something again.
大家不要走啊
Everybody stay where you are.
这次要是捉到贼，一定让他坐牢
If we catch the thief, he's going to jail!
你先站上去
Stand up here.
千万别焦急，有话慢慢说
Don't fret, tell us slow and calm.
大家都听着呀！
Everybody listen!
等等，三六九     有
Wait a minute. 369! -Here!
有没有带手铐来？
You have your handcuffs with you?
带来了     准备拉人
I've got them.   Ready for an arrest.
准备拉人
Get ready then.
好，说吧
OK, tell us.
大家都听着啊
Everybody listen.
我今天下午从外边回来
I came back this afternoon and saw a man
看见有一个人
从楼上匆匆忙忙的下来
running down the stairs hurriedly.
我也觉得有点奇怪
I thought it was a bit strange.
没想到我跑到楼上找东西的时候
Then I went upstairs looking for something,
我不见了一件红旗袍
and found I was missing a red cheongsam,
一件绿旗袍，还有一件丝棉袄
a green one as well, and a silk jacket.
原来是有贼呀
I realised I'd been robbed!
有贼？
Robbed?
有没有见到那人呀？
Did you take a good look at the thief?
我见是没有见到
Not really, but I thought he resembled
不过我觉得那个人的样子
有点像发仔那个死小子
that damned kid, Fat Chai!
你有没有搞错？
Are you sure?
发仔怎会偷东西？
How can Fat hai be a thief?
胡说
Nonsense!
绝对不会是发仔
It couldn't possibly be Fat Chai!
八姑你发神经病啊？
Pat Koo, have you gone crazy?
我整天在做生意怎会偷你的东西
I was working all day, how could it be me?
好了，好了
All right, all right.
发仔有没有偷也用不着吵嘛
Whether it's Fat Chai or not,
吵也没有用嘛
there's no need for a commotion.
三六九在这儿
369 is here.
一搜，不就清楚了吗？
A search will sort everything out.
好，三六九，搜
That's right. A search!
我问你要是搜不着你怎么说？
What if he doesn't find anything?
那些东西明明在里面
The stuff's definitely there.
怎么会搜不到？
How can he not find anything?
你说什么？
What did you say?
不…她是说
No...she simply said...
如果是你偷的东西一定在里边了
if you stole the stuff, it must be there.
好呀，好呀
OK, OK.
我倒不怕你们搜
I'm not afraid of any search.
别吵，别吵
Quiet! Quiet!
如果搜不到怎么说？
But what if he finds nothing?
你不说明我不会让你搜的
Unless that's clear, there'll be no search.
你先说明白，我才让你搜
一定搜得到，你怕什么？
He'll find it. What are you afraid f?
我不是怕，没什么可怕的
I'm not afraid. I've nothing to be afraid of.
你听我说，发仔说的对
Listen to me. Fat Chai's right.
有赏有罚嘛
We must have reward as well as punishment.
不然的话，很容易冤枉好人
Otherwise, the innocent will suffer.
你们说对不对？
Don't you agree?
对对…
That's right.
说明白了
Lets clear the whole thing up.
多余的
好啦，好啦，大家听着
Alright, alright. Listen, everybody.
如果我在里面搜不到那些东西
If I don't find the stuff in there,
我、八姑、三六九我们三个人
then Pat Koo, 369, and I will kneel down
即刻跪在地下向发仔磕三个响头
and kowtow 3 times to Fat Chai.
大家听着，他们搜不到东西来
You heard it. If they find nothing,
三个给我磕三个响头
the'll kowtow to me 3 times!
太子炳，你小心点
Master Bing, be warned.
我是不会放过你的
I'm not letting this go.
放心
Relax.
你看清楚啊，三六九，搜！
Be vigilant, 369. Go!
在哪儿？     籘箱
Where's the stuff? -Rattan basket...
籘箱子
Rattan basket.
阿炳
Ah Bing,
我看发仔这次一定要坐牢了
Fat Chai's going to jail for sure.
我们不如写张招租
Why don't we put up a notice now
把发仔的那个床位给租出去
to let out his bunk space?
你想啊？
You'd like to, wouldn't you?
不过用不着那么急
But there's no need to jump the gun.
等把那个包袱搜出来后也不迟
Wait till 369 finds the bundle of clothes.
八姑，你到底搁在哪里啊？
Pat Koo, where did you put the stuf?
他说什么？
What did he say?
没什么，他说搜了一半
Nothing, he said he's half done.
还有一半没有搜
Another half to go.
你这死人头，这样你都搜不到
Damned idiot! Can't even search right!
整张床位，只有一个破籘箱子嘛
There's only one basket on the bunk!
可是籘箱子里面没有哇
But there's nothing in the basket!
三六九，你怎么这么笨呀
369, how can you be so stupid?
真是莫名奇妙
I can't understand it!
我明明放在这里边的
I put it here myself!
你说什么？     不是
What did you say? -Nothing!
她以为是你把东西放在这里
She thought you put the stuff here.
你…
You...
你有没有弄错
Can you be mistaken?
你不是说亲自放在里边
Didn't you say you put it here yourself?
我怎么会弄错
How could I have got it wrong?
我明明是放在里面的
I definitely put it here!
三六九，不管三七二十一
369, forget it.
把他拉到警察局去
Just haul him off to the police station.
无赃无证，怎么能告他呢
Without proof, how can I charge him?
你就说下午他拿东西去卖了嘛
Just say he sold off the loot this afternoon.
你真够毒的了，难怪你没有儿子
That's wicked! No wonder you have no son!
发仔
Fat Chai!
我现在才明白为什么找不到赃物
I realise why I can't find the loot.
你一定是下午把东西拿去卖了
You must have sold it off this afternoon.
你胡说！     别动！
Ridiculous! -Don't move!
我一进到这里来
As soon as I saw you
就看出你这小子根本不是好人
I knew you were no good.
跟我到警局去！
Come with me to the station!
别吵
Quiet!
想我不拉他，除非他把旗袍拿出来
I won't let him go. Where's the loot?
把旗袍拿出来吧
Hand over the cheongsams!
三六九先生，三六九先生
Mr 369, Mr 369!
拿出来
Hand it over!
那些衣服没有丢啊，全都在这儿
The clothes aren't stolen, they're all here.
你这个死丫头
You damned girl!
打死你
I'll kill you!
红的、绿的，还有丝棉袄
The red one, the green, and the silk jacket.
衣服全在这儿，你们全看见了
They're all here, as you can all see.
你们三个跪下
You three, on your knees!
跪下
On your knees!
什么？你把阿香卖给我们做导游
What? You want to sell us Ah Heung?
是呀
Yes.
我不服这口气，妈的
I can't stand her anymore, dammit!
那个死丫头，吃里扒外
That bloody girl has no family loyalty,
帮着那个臭小子
always taking the side of that damned kid.
八姑
Pat Koo,
你要把阿香卖给我们不值钱呐
she's not worth much to us.
老八，如果价钱不合适就别卖了
If the price's not right, we won't sell.
去你的！你当然不想卖了
Damn you! Of course you don't want to sell!
你想留着自己用了
You want to keep her for yourself!
我才不管，十块也好，二十块也好
I don't care if it's $10 or $20,
反正我非把她卖掉不可
I'm selling her for sure!
等一等…
Wait a minute.
吓死我了
You're scaring me!
我现在给你搭上一条线
I've found you a good connection.
干什么啊？三六九
What is it, 369?
来        拉拉扯扯的干嘛
Come! - Stop pulling! What's the matter?
我一回到分局子里
As soon as I got back to the station house,
就听见分局长嚷着要娶七姨太太
I heard the Chief wants a 7th wife,
声明要十七岁至十八岁
specifically between the ages of 1 7 and 1 8,
我一想就想起阿香来了
so I imediately thought of Ah Heung.
你有没有搞错
You must be joking!
你们分局长有六十多岁了
Your police chief's over 60 years old!
八十岁都要娶
He'll still want it when he's 80.
鬼叫他六个老婆蛋都没生一个
None of his 6 wives has had a child.
老八，分局长立妾等于是徵用吗
Marriage to the chief is like the draft:
不但没有聘礼
he offers no betrothal gifts,
连嫁妆你都要赔进去
so you lose out on the dowry!
炳哥
And you call yourself a man of the world!
真难为你在外面混了这么久
嫁个女儿给分局长
If your daughter marries a Police Chief,
还在乎那点礼金，是不是？
what do you care about betrothal gifts!
你嫁个女儿给分局长
If your daughter marries the Police Chief,
分局长就是你的女婿
he'll be your son-in-law.
将来的好处怎么样
Think of the advantages that'll bring!
你自己去想想好了，想想！
Just think it over!
八姑，这次三六九说得对
Pat Koo, 369's right for a change.
到时候别说赶尽七十二家房客
Never mind evicting your 72 tenants,
就算赶尽全区也没有人敢说话
you can evict the whole district!
怎么会，全城赶尽都行的
Evict the whole city, even!
那也不好
No, that wouldn't do.
如果把全城的人都赶走了
If I got rid of everyone in the city,
就剩我们几个人
there'd just be the few of us left.
那又太冷清了
It'd be too quiet and lonely.
说的是呀！    是呀！
You have a point. -Yes.
三六九，如果这件事成功了
369, if this thing works out,
我一定送你两条大肥猪作为谢聘
I'll reward you two nice plump pigs.
两条大肥猪，油腻太重了吧
Two pigs? That's a bit heavy.
肥猪我是不要啦
You can keep the pigs.
最要紧的是你叫分局长
Just make sure you ask the Chief
替我多挂几条杠就行啦
to put a few stripes on my arm.
别说挂几条
Only a few?
就是挂满了也没问题
You can have an arm full of them!
那你准备办喜事吧
Then you should go make preparations.
真是太缺德
How disgraceful!
把个十九岁的女孩子
Marrying off a 1 9-year-old girl
嫁给一个六十几岁的老头子
to a 60-year-old man!
谁想出这种主意
Whoever came up with that idea
生个儿子也没有屁呀
deserves to have a son with no rear end!
他就是生没屁孩子都生不出来
No rear end? He doesn't deserve a son at all!
如果他能生的话我都生了十个
If he can have a son, I should have 10!
阿香以后的日子怎样过？
What kind of life will it be for Ah Heung?
爸爸，小福硬要我带他去买东西去
Dad, Little Fook wants me to buy him sweets.
好了，好了，别吵了
Okay, settle down.
抱他出去玩玩，快去，快去
Take him outside to paly. Go.
阿福哥
Brother Fook.
福哥，回来了？
You're back, Brother Fook?
阿香怎么了，发仔呢？
How's Ah Heung? Where's Fat Chai?
发仔在楼上陪阿香
Fat Chai's gone up to see Ah Heung.
你们这班臭要饭的
You stinking beggars!
吱吱喳喳地说我什么？
What are you jabbering about?
你快说，你们这群王八蛋
Tell me, you sons of bitches!
今天是我嫁女儿的好日子
You know it's my daughter's wedding day.
你们为什么不来给我道喜？
Why don't you come to congratulate me?
你们都死了？
One would think you'd all died!
八姑，你嫁女都没分钱给我们
They've all gone out to make a living.
他们出去赚钱吃饭嘛
It's not like you're giving out bridal money.
你们全都站在这干什么？想害我
So why are you all here? To plot against me?
八姑，你猜错了
Pat Koo, you've got us wrong.
我们正在商量送东西给你
We're discussing what presents to give.
上海婆要送一张大床
Shanghai Po's giving you a bed.
我呢，准备送一张红木梳妆台
I'm going to give you a chest of drawers.
梳妆台？
A chest of drawers!
陈嫂准备送一打旗袍，是给你的
Mrs Chan's a dozen cheongsams just for you,
不是给阿香，因为你嫁女儿吗？
since you're giving away your daughter.
陈嫂，你要记住腰做小点
Remember to make the waist a bit tighter,
叉开高点
and the slit higher!
还有啊
There's more.
金医生跟韩师母
Dr Kim, the Hans,
还有他们几个邻居
and a few other neighbors
合伙打条三斤重的金链送给你
are ordering a 3-catty gold chain for you.
金医生，让你破费了
Dr Kim, what an extravagance!
这是不好意思
I don't know what to say.
阿福，你们要送礼就早一点送
Ah Fook, you must bring the gifts early,
我呢，好跟你们准备酒席
I've got to prepare a banquet for you.
那可不必啦
Oh, that's not necessary.
那多不好意思
Of course it is.
你们都送那么重的礼
You're giving me so many gifts,
不请不好意思
how can I not invite you?
你听我说嘛
But I haven't finished.
我的橄榄今天又没有卖光
I didn't sell all my olives today,
金医生今天又没有生意
Dr Kim saw no patients,
我们街上又捡不到钱
and we didn't find money on the street.
所以嘛…这个…
So...
说什么？
What are you saying?
所以我们想过还是不送了
So we can't give you anything!
去你的
Damn you!
你们这班的臭东西
You stinking beggars!
大伙儿合起来戏弄我，你们想死
Ganging up to make a fool of me!
好，等我女儿三朝回门那天
Wait till my daughter comes home to visit.
你们就知道厉害
Then you'll see!
八姑，是不是摆十桌酒
Pat Koo, aren't you throwing a 10-table banquet
请我们大家？
to which we're all invited?
十桌酒，吃都把你吃死呀
Ten tables? You'll all be stuffed to death!
酒是酒
I'll throw all right...
到时候你们都得给我走
I'll throw you all out!
发仔，阿香怎么样啦？
Fat Chai, how's Ah Heung?
关着窗户，我看不见她
The windows are closed. I couldn't see her.
就听到哭呀
But I heard her crying inside
我看这样吧，你赶快带阿香走吧
I think you'd best her away from here.
能走就好了，只怕时间来不及了
I wish I could, but it's too late.
老爷，老爷
Sir, sir.
太太，老爷，老爷
Madam. Sir.
来了，马上下来
Coming! Coming right down!
你们这班臭要饭的
You stinking beggars.
赶紧找地方搬家
Get ready to move out,
不然我就拉人
or I'll have you all arrested.
快点啦
Hurry up!
我在锁门
I must lock the door first.
要是让那死丫头跑掉了
If that damned girl escapes,
就鸡犬不宁
we'll be in trouble.
太太
Madam.
是不是分局长来了？
Has the Police Chief arrive?
没有，我看见局长在整理衣服
Not yet. I saw him getting ready
我来通知你们
and came to tell you
叫你们到外面去迎接他
to get ready to welcome him outside.
等他来了好开心一点嘛
That will certainly please him.
是的…走…
Yes, yes. Let's go.
老爷，太太
Sir. Madam.
等回儿见到局长女婿
When you meet your Police Chief son-in-law,
最要紧提一提我的杠呀
don't forget to mention my stripes!
你放心，整堆都有
Don't worry. You'll get a bunch of them.
太太请     老爷请
Madam, please. -Sir, please.
请，请
Please.
笑什么？
What's so funny?
去…
Go on up.
发仔，你上去干什么？
Fat Chai, what are you going up for?
我上去救阿香
I'm going to save Ah Heung.
不要爬水管，拆楼板
Don't climb the pipes or smash floorboards.
阿香…     你…
Ah Heung. -It's you!
我带你走
I'm taking you away.
快
Hurry!
太太，我先去看着
Madam. I'm going to watch out for them.
快，快
Hurry!
阿香来了     阿香
Ah Heung's coming. -Ah Heung.
趁他们现在不在
Take Ah Heung away while they're gone!
你赶快带阿香走吧
我现在不能走
I can't go now!
我走了连累你们大家
I'll get you all into trouble!
你走了不关我们的事
Your going won't have anything to do with us.
你再不走就来不及啦，快点吧
Hurry, go before it's too late!
发仔，我这有点钱
Fat Chai, here's some money.
你赶快带阿香走吧
Take Ah Heung and go!
这里有些钱
Here's some money.
走吧，快点走
Hurry, go!
快点走，快走
你们到什么地方去？
Where are you going?
带阿香走呀
I'm taking Ah Heung away.
不能走呀，八姑已经到了巷口
You can't go. Pat Koo's already in the alley.
真麻烦
Dammit!
早不撒尿，晚不撒尿
What dreadful timing!
这个时候撒尿
金医生，你念过那么多书
Dr Kim, you're an educated man,
想办法救救阿香吧     是
Can't you think of some way to help them?
可惜韩先生到医院排队看病去
Too bad Mr Han's queuing at the hospital,
要不然的话
otherwise there'd be one more person
可以多个人想想办法   是
To help think of what to do. -Yes.
排队看病？
He's queuing at the hospital?
有了，我有办法了
That's it! I've got an idea!
什么办法？
What is it?
慢着
Hang on.
上海婆…这是瓶泻药
Shanghai Po, this is a laxative.
等一会给八姑吃了就行了
Get Pat Koo to take it somehow.
阿香赶快换套男人衣服
Ah Heung, put on some men's clothes.
发仔
Fat Chai,
找张棉被把阿香包起来就行了
wrap her up in a quilt blanket.
包起来？
Wrap her up?
金医生，到底是怎么回事？
Dr Kim, what's all this about?
这你就不懂，来…
You don't understand. Come!
三六九，局长来了你在这等着
369, the Police Chief is coming. Wait here
我跟老八先去办事
I have something to do for Ah Pat.
好，你请
All right. Please.
救命呀！
Help!
他妈的，我今天嫁女儿
Damn it! It's my daughter's wedding!
你要动刀杀人
Are you trying to murder someone?
八姑，这回倒是金医生不对
Pat Koo, Dr Kim's in the wrong this time.
做医生的不给病人看病
A doctor can't refuse to see a patient.
这种病怎么能看
It's not an illness I can treat!
发仔发仔，你也别动刀子
Fat Chai, put down your chopper.
事情是这样的
It's like this.
昨天晚上发仔有个朋友住在这
Fat Chai had a friend stay over last night
今天早上觉得有点不舒服
who didn't feel well this morning,
就请金医生给他看看
so he went to see Dr Kim.
好了，好了，他死是他的事
All right, it's his funeral.
又不关我们的事
None of our business!
你快回去撒尿去吧
Go and take a leak already!
这话可就不对了
That's not right!
你知道他得了什么病吗？
Do you know what disease he's got?
难道得的是霍乱啊
It couldn't be cholera, could it?
就是霍乱
It is indeed cholera!
你再说一次！    是这样…
Say that again? -It's like this.
让我来，我告诉你
Let me tell you what happened.
今天早上我朋友得了病
My friend didn't feel well this morning.
又吐又泻又头晕
He had the runs and felt dizzy,
我请金医生来看一看
so I took him to see Dr Kim.
他告诉我是霍乱
ut he told me it was cholera
说完他就跑了，连看都不看
and wouldn't even take a look.
你说有没有医德？
Doesn' he have any medical ethics?
可是，这种病会传染的
But this disease is contagious!
八姑，这事我们倒不怕
Pat Koo, that's nothing to worry about.
大不了进集中营，对不对
Comes to the worst, we'll just be quarantined.
我最担心就是警察局长到了这儿
But what if the Police Chief finds out?
到时候连阿香都不要了
He may not want Ah Heung anymore!
你想想吧
Think of something!
金医生
Dr Kim!
你这老不死的，连病人都不看
You old bastard! Refusing to treat a patient!
你还算是什么医生？
What kind of a doctor are you?
我告诉你
Let me tell you,
要是我的女儿嫁不出去
if my daughter's wedding falls through,
你看我饶不饶了你
I won't let you get away with it!
八姑，这件事是山东佬的不好
Pat Koo, it's all the Shantung guy's fault!
你也何必生那么大气
Don't upset yourself so.
喝点茶润润嗓子吧
Have a cup of hot tea.
气死我
I'm so mad!
上海婆，这一次你对我最好了
Shanghai Po, you're very kind this time.
应该的，应该的
You deserve it.
死山东佬，你要赶快想办法
Shantung Man, do something quickly!
八姑，这种病是没得救
Pat Koo, it's an incurable disease.
一定死的
He'll die for sure.
你说什么？
What are you saying?
这么说一定要把死尸挺在这儿
You might have to put up with a corpse here.
这可便宜了你，八姑？
What a stroke of luck, Pat Koo!
三朝回门兼做七了
You can have a wedding and a funeral!
去你的，你要赶快想办法
Damn you! Do something, quick!
要不然的话，我就宰了你
Or I'll have your hide for this!
八姑啊
Pat Koo.
救是没得救了，唯一的办法
It's too late to save him. All we can do
就是趁局长没来之前把他搬出去
is get rid of him before the Chief arrives.
不然咱们都没有办法
Otherwise we're all done for. And you, too.
你也是一样，肚子一痛就没救了
Once the stomach cramps start, that's it!
去你妈的，你咒我，真该死
To hell with you! Cursing me to die!
死发仔
Damn you, Fat Chai!
把你的朋友赶快跟我搬走
Get your friend out of here immediately.
你说什么，你就让他见死不救
You mean you won't help a dying man?
算了算了，我怕你了
Alright, alright. You win.
这儿有点钱
Here's some money.
你赶快拿去跟那个病人去看病吧
Take him to see another doctor.
去，去
Go! Go!
发仔，你还不快点带你朋友走
Fat Chai! Take your friend now and go!
好，我搬走
OK, I'm moving out.
金医生，你的这个主意出得真好
Dr Kim, that was a really good idea!
我们全都靠你帮忙了
We really must thank you.
我的主意不错？
My idea's not bad?
正，正
It's great!
让开…传人啊…让开
Make way! Make way! Contagion!
什么事啊？
What's the matter?
你可千万不能进去
Fo heaven's sake don't go in!
那个病鬼得的是霍乱啊
There's a cholera victim!
在局长没有来之前
We must move him out
我们一定要把他抬出去
before the Police Chief arrives.
我现在告诉你
But I came to tell you
分局长的花轿已经到了街口了
his palanquin's has just arrived outside.
让开！
Make way!
阿炳，这怎么办啊？
Ah Bing, what do we do now?
发仔，还不赶快把他抬进去
Fat Chai, get your friend inside quickly!
等会局长来了你想把他抬进花轿
Are you waiting for the Chief's palanquin?
抬进去…
Inside!
那怎么办，如果让分局长知道了
What if the Police Chief finds out?
我们这儿闹霍乱这事情不全完了
If he knows there's cholera here, it's over.
大家听着，等一会局长来了
Listen everybody. When the Chief comes,
任何人不许提霍乱这两个字
don't anyone mention the word cholera!
谁要提了，我就把他枪毙
I'll shoot anyone who does!
你们听见了吗？
Do I make myself clear?
阿炳，我不知是不是心理作用
Ah Bing, I may be imagining it,
我的肚子有点痛
but my stomach hurts.
老八
Ah Pat,
你不能在这时候开我的玩笑
this is no time for jokes!
局长到
The Police Chief!
敬礼！
Salute!
局长大人女婿
Mr Police Chief son-in-law.
坐
Please sit down.
局长大人女婿，早
Good morning. Police Chief son-in-law.
姑爷，老爷、太太给你请安
My greetings, Sir and Madam.
副官，以前那几个怎么叫的？
Officer, what did I use to call the others?
全都是叫爹地、妈咪
You called them Daddy and Mommy.
爹地、妈咪，早
Daddy, Mommy, Good morning.
我们姑爷向老爷太太请安
Our master greets Sir and Madam.
乖，乖
Good, good.
你看我们女婿大人多有礼貌
See how polite our son-in-law is.
你叫什么姐？
What's your name?
我，我叫阿银
I...I'm called Ah Yin.
阿银姐
Ah Yin,
陪我上楼给新娘子换衣服吧
come up with me to help the bride change.
请请
Please.
肚子痛，肚子痛
My stomach hurts!
老婆大人，我的肚子啊
Dear wife, my stomach hurts!
我…我要拉出来了
I...I can't hold it in!
赶快回家吧，快走
Quick, go home!
快走吧，快点回去，走吧
我肚子痛呀
My stomach hurts!
你怎么了？
How do you feel?
我要大便
I must go to the toilet.
你快背我，背我
Carry me. Carry me.
快点
Hurry!
什么事？到底什么事啊？
What's the matter? What's going on?
局长女婿大人，没事
Nothing, Police Chief son-in-law.
绝对没事
Absolutely nothing.
我…
I...
下来了
Coming down
阿炳，你把门锁着干什么
Ah Bing! Why did you lock the door?
老爷，会不会是那玩意啊？
Master, could it be that thing?
不会吧，副官     有
I hope not. Officer! -Yes Sir!
我限你一分钟马上答覆我
You have one minute to find out
这是怎么回事？     是
what's going on here. -Yes Sir.
老家伙     我？
Old man! -Who? Me?
除了你还有谁
Who else but you?
老家伙，我限你三十秒钟内
Old man, you have 30 seconds
答覆我到底这是怎么一回事？
to tell me what's going on here.
不能说啊，炳哥告诉我们
I can't tell you. Ah Bing told us
千万不能提霍乱两个字   霍乱
not to mention the word "cholera". cholera
霍乱？
Cholera?
你这个老不死的
You old bastard!
这谁得霍乱了？谁拉肚子啊？
Who has cholera? Who has diarrhea?
我…拉
I...have...
你这死阿炳
Damn you Ah Bing!
你要是机灵的就给我讲清楚
If you're smart, you'll tell the truth.
你要是不讲老实话
If you don't,
我就判你终身监禁
I'll have you imprisoned for life.
终身监禁
Imprisoned for life?
炳哥，那我不能不说了
Ah Bing, I've got to tell him.
站远点，站远点
Stand back, stand back.
站这儿可以吧   行了，你说吧
Is here all right? -Yes. Speak!
事情是这样的
It's like this. This morning
今天早晨这儿有人得霍乱
someon came down with cholera.
本来我们要把他搬走
We wanted to move him away
可是局长大人娶媳妇
but you were to become a father-in-law,
不，不，做新郎倌
No, no, I mean a bridegroom,
所以现在病人还在我房里
so the patient's still in my room.
三六九
369!
三六九     有
369! -Yes Sir!
限你一分钟内把那霍乱鬼搬出去
You have 1 minute to remove the patient.
是
Yes Sir!
发仔，你去搬吧
Fat Chai, you do it.
你不帮忙，我一个人搬不动
I can't move him without your help.
小心点，病人会传染的
Careful! It's contagious!
看一眼都会传染的，抬脚
Don't even look. Take his legs.
还有
Another thing.
你要是觉得肚子痛就去看医生
If your stomach hurts, go see a doctor.
要不然会死的
Otherwise, you're done for!
谢谢，谢谢你
Thank you. Thank you.
行了吗？   行了
Ready? -Ready.
发仔，有多远走多远
Fat Chai, go as far away as you can.
我知道了，韩师母
I know, Mrs Han.
再见     再见
Goodbye. -Goodbye.
快点走吧
Hurry. Go!
再见…
Goodbye!
发仔，快走，快点…
Hurry up, Fat Chai! Hurry!
你瞧八姑
Take a look at Pat Koo!
你快去   是的，我知道
Hurry! -Yes, I know.
再见了，大家再见了
Goodbye, everyone. Goodbye.
再见了…
Goodbye.
发仔，你还不赶快抬出去
Fat Chai, hurry up and take him outside.
难道等着上花轿吗
You want to wait for the palanquin?
你想得倒美，再见了
What a nice thoght! Goodbye.
再见…
Goodbye.
一四七，二五八   在
147, 258. -Sir!
什么事？
What's the matter?
局长有命令
An order from the Chief.
把这棉被里的东西都扔走
Throw away everything inside this blanket.
这个是什么东西？
What is this?
是不是金器、古董？
Silverware and antiques?
那有那么多金器、古董
How can there be so much of it?
这是霍乱鬼
It's a cholera victim.
你们究竟搬不搬啊？
Are you moving him or not?
不搬我就搬回去了     搬…
If not, I'll take him back. -We're moving!
谁说不搬哪，车，车…
Who says we're not? Pedicab!
叫我？
You calling me?
当然是叫你了
Of course I'm calling you.
有什么事？
What's the matter?
现在要徵用你的车子
We're requisitioning your cab.
把这个棉被和裹着的东西
Take all this as far away as possible.
把它拉走
行，给钱
Okay, but money first.
你这是什么话
What are you saying?
我们徵用你的车还要给钱
Money? We're requisitioning your cab!
不给钱，你凭什么不给钱
No money! Who do you think you are?
你少啰啰嗦嗦的
Shut up. I can charge you with obstructing
我随随便便的可以告你妨碍公务
a police officer in the course of his duty.
你这不是在欺负我吗？
Are you trying to bully me?
你有几个老子你？
How many fathers have you got?
老兄，我朋友得了霍乱
Buddy, my friend has cholera.
要到医院去，求你帮个忙好不好
Get us to the hospital quick, please!
霍乱？有病你们早说嘛
Cholera? Why didn't you say so earlier?
你这人真是开…
The sooner you take him...
要多少钱？
How much?
救人要什么钱
I don't charge for saving lives.
你以为我和他们一样
You think I'm like them?
等救护车来还得等半天，走吧
Can't wait for an ambulance. Let's go.
你胡说八道什么
What are you blabbering about?
你再胡说八道，我抄你的牌
Do you want me to write you a ticket?
他妈的，怎么那么多人恨我们？
Dammit! Why do so many people hate us?
阿炳，怎么样了？
Have they gone, Ah Bing?
我硬把他们推出去了
Yes, I got rid of them.
敬礼！报告局长大人
Salute! Reporting, Chief!
我已经徵用了一辆车
I requisitioned a pedicab
叫他们有多远就把他送多远
and sent them as far away as possible.
局长大人女婿
Police Chief son-in-law.
我可以叫我女儿换衣服了？
Shall I tell my daughter to get dressed now?
快点，快点
Hurry up!
我已经在大三元
I've ordered over 100 tables
订了一百多桌酒席
for the wedding banquet.
快去，快去
Hurry, hurry.
我们现在怎么样了？
What are we going to do now?
不要紧了，我们马上就到火车站
It's OK. We're almost at the train station.
真的？
Really?
阿香…
Ah Heung...
老八…不得了
Oh my goodness, Ah Pat!
你怎么了你？
What's wrong with you?
阿香，阿香不见了
Ah Heung's gone!
阿炳，你说什么？
Ah Bing, what did you just say?
你别吓唬我，我晕过去了
Don't scare me, I'm going to faint.
你可不能晕过去
You can't faint now!
你别开这种玩笑
If that's a joke, it's not funny!
我在大三元订了一百多桌酒席
I've over 100 tables of guests at the restaurant.
能赚很多钱     我知道
That's a lot of gifts. -I know.
你们这帮穷鬼有谁见过阿香？
You beggars! Has anyone seen Ah Heung?
我看见
I saw her.
在什么地方？
Where?
就在这儿
Right here.
什么时候？
When?
昨天晚上
Last night.
去你妈的
Damn you!
三六九   三六九
369. -369.
在…这儿，局…局长，什么事啊
I'm...Here. What...is it, Chief?
我告诉你
I'm telling you.
你今天不把新娘找回来
If you don't find the bride today,
担心你那几条杠
start worrying about your stripes.
我那几条杠怎么样？
What will happen to my stripes?
你等下辈子
You'll get them inyour next life.
我告诉你我知道阿香去了哪儿
I can tell you where Ah Heung is.
去哪儿了？
Where?
前几天你们没听八姑说
Didn't you hear Pat Koo say a few days ago
要把阿香卖到梧州去做妓女吗
she was selling her to Hangchow as a whore?
你这死小子
You bastard!
还要打人
You want to assault me as well?
她一个女儿赚两份钱要打人啊
You're making money twice on your daughter!
来人   来人
Officers! -Officers!
把他们两个给我扣起来
Arrest both of them.
把他们两个扣起来     是
Arrest both of them. -Yes sir!
老八
Ah Pat!
局长大人女婿
Police Chief son-in-law!
你千万别听那些王八蛋的话
don't listen to those bastards.
你看我的长相，我就跟菩萨一样
Look at me. I look like a bodhisattva.
我一点坏事都不会做的
How can I be a bad person?
再加上你长得这么风流潇洒
Plus you're such devastatingly handsome,
不但阿香想嫁给你
it's not just Ah Heung who wants to wed you,
连我都想嫁给你了
even I want to marry you myself!
老八，老八
Ah Pat, Ah Pat.
你等一等啊
Wait a minute.
副官
Officer.
反正今天晚上也没有新娘敬酒
Since I need a bride tonight anyway,
她也不错
this one's not too bad.
那是岳母呀，也要？
But she's your mother-in-law!
我可没试过
I've never tried one before.
那就试试吧，抓她妈     是
I might as well give her a go. -Yes Sir
上轿     是！
Palanquin! -Yes Sir!
救命呀！
Help!
老八
Ah pat!
你想溜啊
Don't try to get away!
走！
Let's go!